<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-09-13T17:42:40+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">after the exhibition (october 2023)</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/exhibition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="after the exhibition (october 2023)"/><published>2024-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/exhibition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/exhibition/"><![CDATA[<style>img{float:left;border:1px dotted black;margin:0 20px 10px 20px}body{text-alignment:justified</style> <p>&lt;/head&gt;</p> <body> <h2 style="margin:0px 20px 15px 20px">After the exhibition</h2> <p><img src="https://marialaurids.net/assets/blog_posts/posts/aftertheexhibition.jpeg.jpg" width="50%" height="50%"/> What came back to me after reading his story out loud, overwhelmed with emotion:</p> <p>• I think that writing is constantly failing at what you love.</p> <p>• The magic of us, what we can do together.</p> <p>• Flashbacks of Prague in February, being alone but knowing that there was someone waiting for me. The last months before leaving home, all of its beauty and horror, the terrifying unending hours of preparation, the time carved away for my friends. The last week; singing with Ivan at the night, the hours at the bars which advanced slowly. The month I lived with Bea and I felt the pull to stay, to move a little closer. Beginning of October, when my brother came to visit in my student dorm and we walked alongside the same life for a little while again. The morning I arrived in Paris, tired and confused, and Saou picked me up from the station and put together a huge breakfast that went on for hours. The sunlit evenings of the first lockdown, when I forced myself to write every night and something came out of that, too, even if it didn’t have to.</p> <p>• The night me and Coco rejoiced over learning that we had used the same word to describe the particular electricity of the exhibition, magic. It’s not an uncommon word, maybe not one a writer should use proudly. But that evening I was drunk and sentimental and I have to protect that, too: the feeling of wonder of both of us having carved the same word to describe that same feeling. While the conversation went on, I browsed my phone and then showed Coco the first draft of this, the word ‘magic’ right at its beginning, as evidence, as proof.</p> <p>• I’ve been thinking a lot about memory, my hometowns. In my first year in Berlin it was the sea that lapped my thoughts most frequently. It was the first element of my life in Italy I tried to turn into symbol, folding layers of meaning on top of each other: pictures, lines from poems, the words of friends, too, born by the sea, to make a figure of my own. All along the sea was there, unchanged, and the after-image of me and my brother staring out into it before he left. Me, wondering when meaning would kick into place, fill the experience. Now that my heart is bound to others which bind me to Berlin, I’ve started remembering the narrow, internal streets of Pozzuoli, the ample ones of Naples, opening (with a sudden gasp) into a sudden sky, the sea. What does missing mean? It’s just the heart adjusting. During my first year, I lied to my heart and let it reminisce, because the jump had been hard. Half here, half there. Promising to come back, to myself, to others - until it didn’t matter anymore. </p> <p>• I’ve weaved my heart in with yours. How long for doesn’t matter. Ribbons from yours are interlaced with mine. Traces: I hope you feel the same. </p> <p>• Something in my heart shifted, like an old cosmic mechanism commanding the eclipses and the seasons of the moon, as I read the last words of Tommaso. I knew then that, for all my rush, my imprecisions, my shortcomings, the slips of my pen and my accent, the ritual had been successful. I knew then, as certainly as I know that it is me who was speaking, that Tommaso is alive, that we did it, me and him.</p> <p>• One day the sum of the exhibition will rise again over me and I will remember.</p> <p>• That evening and days later me and Coco talked about the specific shapes of this magic and found them to be, again, synchronous. To each of us a narrative. The one I’ve landed on: the magic was the magic. You should’ve been there. And this magic was the magic of us. Of our time: the days and the particular moment of our meeting, the few months we shared. The magic is the magic of us, doing the thing we love, out of love. This magic was all around us and it came and went in waves, because pure, continuous feeling is unsustainable, but it never went away. It reached its highest – the point of maximum concentration – when I read Tommaso’s words for the second time, having gathered my words and my love. Then, afterwards, when we hosted the second guided tour for strangers who, in one day, would live to see three, four exhibitions, who knows how many objects, how many labours of love. We guided them, as we were required to, but I felt that no one else was let in on the secret, the magic that we shared, because that’s not something you can give away and because we’re petty like that. And we really were like children, swimming around, in and out of the swarming schools of strangers, hyping up those for whom the time had come to stand alone and explain, in front of the public, with words reasonable and intimate enough their work, until the moment was over, the light moved away, and we were reabsorbed into our little group to be congratulated and held. Always a good word, a work of love.</p> <p>• Happiness feels like honey dripping into the heart. I find out happiness gifts time back and I go out of our group to see my friends, my boyfriend, to send messages to the absent and to the unwilling, because I need to tell everyone.</p> </body> <p>&lt;/table&gt;</p> <p>&lt;/body&gt;</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[&lt;/head&gt;]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">storia di tommaso</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/storia-di-tommaso/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="storia di tommaso"/><published>2024-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/storia%20di%20tommaso</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/storia-di-tommaso/"><![CDATA[<p>Exhibition with <a href="https://www.agatahoerttrich.com/queerthingstaketime">Agata Hörttrich</a>, Coco Wiss, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/ezehyon/">Ezequiel Hyon</a>, <a href="https://bueronoelle.com/">Jean-Noël Teschauer</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/jilschuberth/">Jil Schuberth</a>, Lu Herbst, <a href="http://lulabornhak.com/">Lula Bornhak</a>, <a href="https://majazagorska.com/">Maja Zagórska</a>, Mascha Naumann, <a href="https://mattiafriso.com/">Mattia Friso</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/targetlady/">Richard Müller</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/scek_art/">Steve C.E. Knoll</a> and <a href="https://veramariedeubner.com/">Véra Marie Deubner</a>.</p> <p>Storia di Tommaso is a performative story that attempts to tell a queer narrative of becoming, finding identity and purpose outside of the frames of linear storytelling and timelines. Result of the Queer Things Take Time workshop and exhibited in the omonimous exhibition in September 2023, it is a novella informed by concepts of queer temporalities. Set in the first part of the 20th century in South Tyrol, the story is told over multiple languages and perspectives of witnesses to one man’s story who, during the Italian colonisation of the land and its subsequent attack on Ethiopia, tried to define himself across the the frames and temporalities of Christianity and Italianess.</p> <p><em>First cluster: prologue / part V: the gospel of Tommaso / epilogue</em></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster1-1.JPG-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster1-1.JPG-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster1-1.JPG-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster1-1.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Introduction and conclusion to the story with words from the heart of the story, Tommaso's perspective. Installation with writing desk: candle, writing machine, writing paper, portrait and devotional image. Chair, jacket, and string from which the pages hung. At the side of the typewriter, a page invited comments and especially continuations of the story. Some five additions were made by visitors and hung alongside the other pages. </div> <p><em>Second cluster: part I: days of halcyon / part II: body</em></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster2-1.JPG-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster2-1.JPG-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster2-1.JPG-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster2-1.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Tommaso and Johannes' childhood in South Tyrol. Account by Johannes in German, mine in English. Arranged in a tree-like pattern, growing 'sideways'. </div> <p><em>Third cluster - part IV: Bekehrung</em></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster3-1.JPG-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster3-1.JPG-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster3-1.JPG-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster3-1.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Three accounts of Tommaso's conversion in German, English, Italian. Arranged in a spiral-like movement. </div> <p>Collages for the collective <em>Queer Things Take Time zine booklet</em>, one for each session of the workshop: queer apocalypse; queer childhood; queering the archive; queering the public space.</p> <div class="row mt-4"> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine1-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine1-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine2-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine2-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine3-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine3-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine3-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine4-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine4-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine4-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine4.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exhibition with Agata Hörttrich, Coco Wiss, Ezequiel Hyon, Jean-Noël Teschauer, Jil Schuberth, Lu Herbst, Lula Bornhak, Maja Zagórska, Mascha Naumann, Mattia Friso, Richard Müller, Steve C.E. Knoll and Véra Marie Deubner.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">invocation - autofiction *</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/invocation-autofiction-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="invocation - autofiction *"/><published>2024-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/invocation-autofiction-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/invocation-autofiction-1/"><![CDATA[<p>You wake up in the middle of the night – my long-time friend, my other half. You wake in the middle of the night because something has broken the rhythm of your sleep: a distant howl, maybe, a call for some closeness that you too can feel, a sudden thirst. Somebody walks by in the corridor and their approach takes you out of the dream, takes you by surprise when you’re still unable to defend yourself. Now you’re afraid that something is coming and that you cannot stop it and this fear plunges you underwater, where you cannot breathe. But the steps continue beyond your door, and you’re safe again. You could try and sleep some more– you feel the temptation of being lulled back into that sweet nothingness where you don’t have to question your desires and where the memory and fantasies of the boy you once were blend together. But something of the dream’s horniness has stayed with you, and it keeps you awake – a vibration in your body, a distinct arousal; a desire to move the sheets. You wish to come back to that state of youthful bliss, but it’s too late, your mind is slowly finding its way back to you. It now catches up on what your body already knew: that warmth close to you. Something of the dream’s infinite possibilities has stuck with you and you start remembering your dream, green glass shards of a story that first disgusts, then excites you. Memories of the evening that was and the fantasies you have kept inside of you so long, no one to confide them to.</p> <p>over at <a href="https://translucentgreenplasticpress.com/invocation-autofiction-1/"><em>translucent green plastic press</em></a>. Edited by Jonah Lubin and Mona Thierse. Published 08 May 2023.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You wake up in the middle of the night – my long-time friend, my other half. You wake in the middle of the night because something has broken the rhythm of your sleep: a distant howl, maybe, a call for some closeness that you too can feel, a sudden thirst. Somebody walks by in the corridor and their approach takes you out of the dream, takes you by surprise when you’re still unable to defend yourself. Now you’re afraid that something is coming and that you cannot stop it and this fear plunges you underwater, where you cannot breathe. But the steps continue beyond your door, and you’re safe again. You could try and sleep some more– you feel the temptation of being lulled back into that sweet nothingness where you don’t have to question your desires and where the memory and fantasies of the boy you once were blend together. But something of the dream’s horniness has stayed with you, and it keeps you awake – a vibration in your body, a distinct arousal; a desire to move the sheets. You wish to come back to that state of youthful bliss, but it’s too late, your mind is slowly finding its way back to you. It now catches up on what your body already knew: that warmth close to you. Something of the dream’s infinite possibilities has stuck with you and you start remembering your dream, green glass shards of a story that first disgusts, then excites you. Memories of the evening that was and the fantasies you have kept inside of you so long, no one to confide them to.]]></summary></entry></feed>