<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-06-16T11:59:57+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">barndomsfragment 2 (lilla huset part I)</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2025/konrad2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="barndomsfragment 2 (lilla huset part I)"/><published>2025-06-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2025/konrad2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2025/konrad2/"><![CDATA[<style type="text/css">.more_info{border-bottom:1px dotted;position:relative}.more_info .title{position:absolute;top:20px;background:#f5b49d;color:#3e3f47;text-align:center;padding:6px;left:0}</style> <p><i>Och med till Konrad Karlsson.</i> May 2024_June 2025. You can read the first part <a href="marialaurids.net/blog/2024/konrad1">here</a>.<br/> TW: childhood abuse, though without any specific description. <br/> 🌹 Sometimes, as I dozed off on the bus from Krumme Lanke to my room in Schlachtensee, I found myself thinking back to the child I was: this intruder, this unknown, this obstinate dissonance in my story, a ‘him’ refusing being dealt away with. I had just changed my name, my tongue, my home. One year before I met you, before Mårran or Troll I Kulisserna, I found myself stuck between this sudden need to remember and the scarceness of my memories, the hardness of those that had coagulated around silence, unspeakability. I started looking for a frame for him, something to hold him in place, together, before he disappeared again. I watched Petite Fille and I found a <i>her</i>, then something else, running alongside him, children and phantoms sharing the same game, the same running. The semester you and I met was quite calm; in the following, I read about queer temporalities for the first time and, at the QTTT workshop, I found out that it had already been written about the child. It was what I needed – for myself, for him, for Mignon.</p> <p>On September 9th 2022 we went on our first date. We had been talking for two weeks before that; you wanted to wait until you felt better in order to meet and I appreciated your patience, you asking me for the same. One of our running disagreements is about when our relationship started. You mention May 2023, when we verbalized, semi-contractually, its begin. But I knew on September 10th, when you woke up at my place and we went to get breakfast, that I wanted to be with you, as well as that we’d end up together. To honor that feeling, in retracing the steps of our relationship, I don’t waste any time and let it begin the day we met.</p> <p>Fifteen years before that, queer theories had discussed the meaning of the <i>future</i>. Leo Bersani and Lee Edelmann, arguing for other, more positive investments of queer life energy, both interestingly argued against the child as well, seen as the political vanguard of conservative, homophobic thinking: an obstacle to queer futures. At the same time, José Esteban Muñoz tried to redeem the value of the future (and hope and utopian feeling) and Kathryn Bond Stockton focused on the child itself, asking: <i>what is a child</i>, after all, before its political instrumentation? What is a child really, to itself? How can we think about children inside the frame of queer theory?</p> <p>Stockton’s discourse begins with a fundamental distinction between child and Child <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>: between actual, living (‘historical’) children and the ideological category of the Child, the shared, general idea of what a child is, can, and should be. Every real living child is confronted and understood in comparison with this fantasy of an ideal Child. Going back to Edelmann, in his book “No Future” he actually takes a stance not against children, but against the Child, which he sees as a political plan to secure the future exclusively through (heterosexualist <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>) reproduction, in terms of literal, biological continuation of the human species. This Child, objective and symbol of this plan, is shaped after the ruling political class whose survival it must safeguard: undoubtedly white, cissexual and straight, imagined as a powerless, a-sexual being in need of constant protection (from the threats of contact and violence from people different by race, sexuality, gender identity and expression, class). I imagine this Child as a smug, well-educated, white suburban child (the likes of which I’ve never seen, who exist mostly in movies). Any other child: racialised <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, sexual, non-straight, non-conforming to rules of gender, is not granted this security, is excluded (at all or at times) from the category of the Child, from the white matrix, denied general, widespread empathy, care, protection<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>. <span class="more_info" title="Did you feel safe in your childhood?">Kände du dig trygg i din barndom?</span> Who protected you, and from what? I must’ve been safe because I am white, passed as straight. But it still didn’t feel safe. <span class="more_info" title="In which ways were you allowed or not allowed to be a child?">På vilka sätt kände du att du tilläts vara ett barn?</span></p> <p>As much as Edelmann argues for worthwhile resistance against the Child and its political underpinnings, it is Stockholm I feel really drawn to, because she centers the life and experiences of real, living children in her discourse; because, in doing so, she brings me much closer to the child I actually was. I want to understand him, I want to bring him back, I want to do something of childhood, with childhood, I want its passing to not have been in vain. But even once we separate child from Child, we still are no closer to understanding what it really is. This is because “child” is itself an ineffective definition: it works only in negative terms, indicating a non-adult characterized by innocence (understood in a more or less secular Christian way as absence of sexuality, then of sin). What is a child, then? Who is that person I remember, who I must’ve been, at some point? The more questions are asked, the clearer does it become that this <i>reduction of meaning</i> we call a ‘child’ cannot account for the complexity of the life of that which we were: the «pleasures and terrors we recall»<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>, the shadows of (pre?)sexuality, the tangled, inexplicable feelings that are too big for words, which almost seem to take one outside of childhood. Which maybe did so back then already. A child is a simplification, but it didn’t feel like that in its time, when childhood was a body and a succession of days and not a memory, a more or less disjointed piece of fossil. Somewhere between being a child and remembering the child, in growing up, the transmission of meaning goes wrong: we grow out of childhood, we forget <i>what that felt like</i>, the names we called ourselves with and, as we settle on the placating definition of ‘child’, <span class="more_info" title="a climate of suspicion, unspeakability, loss, still comes to hover over the real childhoods we had ">ett misstänksamt klimat, obeskrivligt, förlust, svävar fortfarande över den faktiska barndomen vi haft.</span>. Looking for clues in a child’s understanding of itself seems to be in vain, too: self-definition is obstructed by legal and social traditions that decide what a child is and should be (that is to say, shaping the idea of the Child). This becomes even harder for those we, backwardly, call queer children: when the vocabulary of queerness, of sexual difference, is not made available to the child (reeking, as it does, too strongly of sex, of perversion, which are adult prerogatives), how can a child express its perceived difference with its surroundings? Stockton finds a surprising abundance of emotional identifications and metaphors flourishing from children, lapping on this very impossibility: one calling himself «a homosexual seagull» (1), another identifying with a butch plumber in an ad. These weird and aslant expressions do their best to evade the cage of the Child, of childhood. <span class="more_info" title="What did you call yourself? Was ‘gay’ attractive or painful to you?">Vad sade du om dig själv? Var “bög” attraktivt eller kanske sårande för dig?</span>. I stayed in the safety of being unnamed as long as I could. I measure the extent of the violence also by this fact: that I already knew, always knew, that to give yourself a name or allow yourself to be named is to be made visible, and to be made visible is to be revealed, to be put in danger. I still ask myself how could I have known this. Was the threat so widespread as to inform every thought and behavior, or is there an opposite to growing up - <i>time travel?</i> Did I, as I am and know today, somehow go back and explain to myself the rules of survival? Isn’t this the God Augustine calls to – the one who calls back, this conscience that is most easily explained, and experienced, in writing? <span class="more_info" title=" Do you see what I mean? Do you see what I mean somewhat more clearly, now?">Förstår du var jag menar? Ser du vem du var tydligare nu?</span> These are the hardships we face if we try to define what a child is. Because of them, Stockton asks: is there, actually, such a thing as a child? Can we really find a definition for it? <span class="more_info" title=" You - did you ever feel like a child? What did that mean to you?"> Du - kände du dig som ett barn? Vad betydde det för dig?</span> Whatever way we approach it, there is an essential complexity to childhood – a contrast between memory and experience, between experience and its understanding, between complexity and the simplification (with all of its underlying violence). Stockton concludes there is only one possible definition of the child that bears witness to this complexity: a child is «precisely who we are not and, in fact, never were» (5). She writes, dishearteningly: it is nothing but <i>«the act of adults looking back»</i> (5, emphasis mine). It is exactly this gesture, this failure, this holding of complexity, which interests me, because it risks explaining what I felt. Ultimately, Stockton articulates the identity of the/a child by marking its distinction from the Child, yes, distinguishing between being a child and what it is wanted to be, but, most importantly, <i>in and through the architecture of memory</i>: in the difference between who we are and who we remember. Children, confined in straightjackets of definitions, explained only through negations, with their own words being obstructed or not listened to, suffer severe consequences: «such a child, with no established forms to hold itself in the public, legal field, <i>has been a child remarkably, intensely unavailable to itself in the present tense</i>» (6, my emphasis). We cannot understand what a child is to itself, because the child itself doesn’t know. From the vantage point of memory, a child appears as a strange being between adulthood and whatever comes before it, caught between its own perception, its own attempts at self-definition, and the invasive gaze of others: a changeling, the <i>bortbyting</i> of which the stories of your culture are full of. For some of us (for myself) at some point during the life of a child the body, the space of feeling and experience, becomes inaccessible, and it’s a life’s work to regain it. What we call a child is ultimately the result of a «backward birth» (6): this act of looking back into the being we were and are no more, a retroactive creation installed in the processes of recollection, between the layers of this one body which becomes double. The layers of childhood multiply not just because of the unavailability of the body, but because of the split between child and Child.<br/> I am trying to articulate here, through Stockton’s essay, a definition of childhood as a «membrane»: an interstitial space, a void in-between, a mezzanine which is barely accessible to the child, but «largely available to adults as memory» (5). During this time the Child imposes itself like a second skin<sup id="fnref:5:1"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>, hardly distinguishable from the first one, with all of its pressures and limitations, dictating what a child is, what it must not become. A troubling degree of voyeurism haunts this definition: the child spies through the keyhole of the Child (its body and its memory) into others, different children and the space of living they are afforded, into the mysterious life of adults, and into itself, its own life, body, experiences. As I move across my memories, I try to revive them, to make sense of what happened, to access this membrane of childhood, the «pleasures and terrors» woven in its fabric – the memories, real or not, of the Mumin beheading, which were formed in my adult years, that vast blue silence I can still remember, all of the things I can’t say yet – <span class="more_info" title="I am not returning to the child, but inventing it.">Jag återvänder inte till barnet, utan uppfinner det.”</span> That child was not accessible to himself, is not accessible to me now. I cannot find him, but I can create the next-best thing, a rhetorical chimera half memory half speculation, as I describe him with a vocabulary of feeling and identity that is available only to me, only in the afterwards, having reached ‘adulthood’. &lt;span class=”more_info” title=”I am writing now to find that child.”&gt;Jag skriver nu för att hitta det barnet&lt;/span&gt;.<br/> And the child changed too, over the years – depending on the time of access, as my understanding of myself changed, as it became necessary to either install or rescue strands of emotions and thought that I either see continuing now, in the aftermath, or remember the isolated ones, existing in the vacuum of childhood. Said with Stockton, the child is ultimately an effect of memory, as intangible as the latter is, an ever-imperfect attempt to resolve this complexity we feel, as well as the first queer autobiographical question: «when did you know?» (2). This matter can hardly be settled, and approached only retroactively, by turning one’s gaze towards the past which couldn’t be defined in the time of its presence. Only as an adult can I look back; and this child must die, give way to me, to the adult years, for me to be able to call him queer. His death must be accompanied by another death: that of what Stockton calls the “straight child”, an aspect of the Child structure with a particular highlight on the pressures and expectations that are supposed to catapult the child from its presumed a-sexuality to open heterosexuality (the only accepted outcome). In order for me to even attempt the retrieval of the queer child, to face the grief and loss which trouble his face in my memories, I must declare the death of this straight child. And still, I find nothing but the aftershades of an unknown who lived desperately, proficiently, in lack and in need of words, in hiding. It is only at a basic removal, at some distance – an international move, so many years of forgetting – that I might be able to reconcile myself with him, to give him the space he needed. <span class="more_info" title="How far I have to go to find you – changeling child.">Hur långt måste jag gå för att hitta dig - bortbyting</span>There is, of course, a significant amount of arbitrariness to this. How can I say with any certainty: <span class="more_info" title="&lt;i&gt;I was a queer child?&lt;/i&gt; Were you? Can anyone be?"> <i> jag var queer som barn?</i> Var du? Kan någon vara det?</span> Every language proves insufficient, every vocabulary fails. I always had, like most children, complex desires for touch, proximity, affection, and they extended to both little girls and little boys. I don’t know if that’s enough to invoke queerness. I cannot know of my gender, either; if my sense of being non-binary today (this refusal of loud, brawling masculinity, of the violence it prokes and sustains, this move towards gender expansion) can be traced back to my little games and aversions; I don’t know if I can extend my current understand of myself this far into the past. Looking back, I’ve found hints, not one proof. I can’t say anything for certain – whether I was or wasn’t a boy, if I wanted to be; if boyhood ever meant anything to me or if it was just the hide that would keep me the safest. <span class="more_info" title="My memories shift and spill like watercolour, and I don’t know where to begin.">Mina minnen skiftar och spills ut som vattenfärger, och jag vet inte vart jag skall börja.</span> Stockton’s discourse, in her intentional, sweeping generalization of childhood as queer, pays the just tribute to the complexities of childhood; to the very real experience of layered and conflicting feelings, oblique and cross desires that (this somehow I remember so clearly) occur daily in a child’s mind, before we must learn to give it confines, before the walls are made to rise, so much taller than us. In this light, recollection appears as the process that not only brings memories back to ourselves, but as the desperate attempt to re-inhabit the space between who we were and are, between the remembering adult and the sought child, and also the <i>membrane</i> between the child and the Child, the space of experience of the child itself, where feelings were felt and the memories (which now constitute our access point) were produced. But we must declare this process impossible, too. Recollection always fails: as in the double story of Troll i Kulisserna, the memories are volatile, ever-changing, prone to defect, corruption. The child remains unexplainable, inaccessible. (I believe in this. But I know there’s different degrees of unfathomability to childhood. Maybe there are some truths about yours: memories you feel you can trust. But that’s not true for me, and I know I’m not the only one<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup>. I have forgotten (had to) so much that was essential to my sense of who I was, and the few memories that remain are all terrible, and I can’t look at them yet. All of this (my work on childhood, my relationship with myself, with you, with that child) rests on a simple fact: &lt;span class=”more_info” title=”I’m not sure what happened.”&gt;Jag är osäker på vad som hände&lt;/span&gt;. Or: <i>I was made not to be sure of what happened.</i> I had to forget, to distance myself from the event, from memory.<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>) In trying to define childhood as a membrane, in looking at the process of remembering/creating the child, I do not mean to prove an essentialist<sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup> sense of queerness, a timeline in which childhood leads directly into my present now. I do not care to call that child queer because I want to understand myself as queer now – but because the queerness I believe in is a way of kinship, of connection. If I were a queer child, what (or who) can I connect that child with? What memories suddenly make sense now, when linked with my understanding of queerness of today? What theories might I use to understand him - what do they say, productively, helpfully, about him? &lt;span class=”more_info” title=”What story about him can I write?”&gt;Vilken historia kan jag skriva om honom?&lt;/span&gt;. I do not remember enough. I need a hook and I’m using theory as one. (Among others: Mumin, writing, you). The result is this impossible answer – or rather, this multiplication of answers, all imperfect, all temporary, which give way into these words I try to give you. Sharpening a definition of <i>child</i> that accounts for this complexity, for the apparently perverted games that children play, for their “pleasures and terrors”, also makes space for the desire my generation, as the last one that grew between the offline and the online, when the Internet was still mysterious, both infinite and very small, for finding the scary and the traumatizing in the medias of our childhood, between proto-Youtube and school courtyard tales. I cannot claim any of the Mandela effects that could’ve been accessible to me as an Italian kid growing up in the early 2000s, but I remember other moments: reading scary stories online on Italian blogs (bad translations, still effective), being terrorized by forcing myself to watch late-night TV documentaries on the seven apparitions of Mary, the Mothman or reptilians; accessing the chunky Youtube page of the time to watch videos about Lavender Town, always looking over my shoulder to not be caught, being scared sleepless of its implications, that I would die of frequencies that only a child could hear. Then, years later, I would find out about Troll i Kulisserna/Mumintrollet and invest in it so deeply that I couldn’t help but write about it – the draft from which all of this started. <span class="more_info" title="What does this say about me, about my childhood? Where do I go from here?">Vad säger det om mig, om min barndom? Vart tar jag vägen härifrån?</span> <span class="more_info" title="Terror was the easiest way I could reach myself.">Terror var det enklaste sättet jag kunde nå mig själv på.</span> Nothing brought me back to my body as efficiently as night sweats, extending my eyes into the room at night to see what I wanted to see, what I feared I would see, what I needed to protect myself from. Playing with turning the TV on and off, closing and opening the creepypasta blogs - fort, da. Mask on, off. Stockton touches only lightly on trauma, and does so in reference to Freud’s theory of <i>Nachträglichkeit</i>, his original understanding of trauma as a “deferred action”, an impression, an event that is impossible for the (child) brain to process and incorporate, and consequently remains hidden in the mind. This unprocessed knot of feelings and memories can later be <i>activated</i> during a similar traumatic event or during psychoanalysis (in the classical, Freudian sense of analysis of the deep). Only through this activation is the original traumatic event constructed, <i>retroactively</i> (nachträglich), as traumatic, and its latent effect (protecting the psyche by avoiding situations that could have reopened the wound) becomes seen, understandable, and possible to integrate and overcome. Like the child, trauma is created posthumously, in the afterwards, by remembering, looking back. Stockton remarks a fundamental difference: the child can be aware of this state of deferral, of its delay – it might « await only (the right to claim) a word, not a mental state of being, withheld from them in childhood. » (15). <span class="more_info" title="As a child I was terribly aware of myself.">Som barn var jag så förfärligt självmedveten.</span> I was desperate, reckless, to grow up: I walked away from anything childish, from any diminutives, any -ino (from myself, too, as a bambino); I insisted on inflating my vocabulary with big, abstruse words, and delighted when the adults, halfway buying my performance, confided in me. I was trying to grow up as quickly as possible. I shifted into a space within me where, in hiding, I could observe children and adults, studying their mannerisms, the topics of their conversations, to learn how to emulate or avoid them. The result of my efforts was a grotesque parody of an adult, something somber, saddening and slightly troubling – more <i>bortbyting</i> than child. I started to think of myself as an adult in a child’s body, because (I reconstruct now) there was no space for me to hold my feelings and remain a c/Child. Today I can’t help but see the dangers of being perceived as older. <span class="more_info" title="I don’t know if this was a consequence of the abuse or a prelude to it.">Jag vet inte om det var en konsekvens av misshandel eller en inledning till det.</span> Eventually, when the first hairs started poking out of my upper lip, I celebrated a sad victory – already knowing that, though an era of powerless was coming to its end, becoming a boy would bring its unique and terrifying consequences, too (how could I have known already?). That it wasn’t over. When I look back to my memories, my point of view hangs far above my eyes, somewhere above my head. It’s always been like this. I cannot tell whether this is a consequence of the emotional and physical dissociation that that child experienced or an aftereffect of my distance as an adult, which I now install into the past. I see myself as if I were walking by his side, a vaporous conscience above him. I cannot define who he was without acknowledging where I’m throwing my gaze from now, and that there wouldn’t be an adult without a child who, despite everything, including himself, made it through. There wouldn’t be a child without me to remember him. We create each other, depend on the other to exist. Being a child, living inside this membrane, <span class="more_info" title="at the same time inside and outside childhood">i samma stund inuti och utanför barndomen</span> meant living halfway here, halfway then. Never fully in one place, never able to produce a clear, incontestable memory. This membrane, the space he retreated inside of, the difference between me and him, becomes the access point to the life I had, to the dreams we sheltered inside there. He dreamed of the man he would become, of the year he would escape. I dream of being able to save him. But what happened did. <span class="more_info" title=" I lost the child, I lost memory">Jag förlorade barnet, Jag förlorade minnet.</span> 🌹 We talk about this. We spend a long afternoon, then a long evening, trying to translate all of this into your first tongue, rushed by a deadline I wasn’t careful enough to anticipate. I sit on the sofa, or on the bed, you are at your desk, working away. Sometimes (sometimes only) you ask me what I mean with this or that. I try to tell you, but the afternoon’s fight still weighs on my ability to explain myself. I don’t want to do this anymore. You insist, I tell you. Every other time we talked about me writing about my childhood, about us, and you translating it, you sounded excited. I was happy to see you involved, interested in my work. But this is not what I wanted. You resent me for this. I don’t feel much already anymore. It will take me a long time – after this, after Gotland – to realize that I had messed up my expectations, the workload. That I hurt you as much, if not more, as I hurt myself. Because I couldn’t just tell you: will you look at this thing I wrote? It’s for you. It’s about you. I want you to be part of it, too. I want our names to exist together, next to each other, on the page. See what happens next. 🌹 We fought once and, in the crying and reconciling that comes afterwards, you were pointedly honest and said something that I hadn’t thought would hurt me. Then, to my surprise, a breathlessness rose in my chest and I observed myself running to the bathroom, locking myself in there. The camera of memory follows me from above, like nature documentary. <span class="more_info" title="You ran after me and waited outside, terrified.">Du sprang efter mig och väntade utanför, förskräckt.</span> Inside, I dealt with the first panic attack of my life. In the mist-like texture between memory and experience, the words you said on the sofa had curiously mixed themselves with my mother’s voice. When I got out, you looked at me with so much sadness in your eyes and apologized. I was delighted. The panic your words caused in me proved two things: first, that our relationship had alchemized that unique balance of safety and challenge which allows us to keep moving; secondly, the existence of something <i>true</i> inside myself, a feeling of hurt so deep and unquestionable that it had to mobilize the whole body to work through it. It proved that I have been hurt – that the memories were not wrong; <span class="more_info" title=" that they could be awakened - by you."> att dom kunde väckas till liv - av dig.</span> 🌹 I never really looked at that picture. We had plenty at home but this is the only one which, for some reason, I have on my computer, which means, with me after the move. In it, he’s playing a little violet plastic piano, my brother a silver saxophone, also plastic. I can’t tell if I’m smiling, smirking, or looking a little afraid at the camera. It changes every time I look. The more I do, the more that face distorts into a vague disturbing blankness. We are standing in front of our desk, right in front of the one that, years later, would become mine. We never changed them. At sixteen he would go on to write his first stories on that desk then, a few years later, prepare for the German exam that would allow him to leave. He used to hide under there as a kid. I would put my face against the little space between the desk and the wall, where a little cold air draft would come through, and breathe really slowly. So as not to make a sound. I cry for a few seconds, then it’s over again. 🌹 Notes for another attempt, another life: a child is a mumin and a mumin is a child. 🌹 I am in the room. It’s the haunted house up the hill, the ruins of the farmhouse he dreamed of. In classic house horror fashion, the walls are alive and semi-transparent, beating softly like a heart: I can see the flickering of a flame in the other room, moving in rewind, I hear an inverted breath, a voice counting from ten to zero, or the other beings that walk the halls. For decades, faces have been appearing all across the house on the walls, on its rocky floors, slightly shifting shade, expression, and nobody really knows what’s going on, if I’m making them up or not. A team of researchers has finally come to prove me wrong, but I do not care. I just let them in. I have gotten to the final room, the basement or the attic, the revelation of the secret, the twisted logic behind the story. I rest my head against the wall which is is a womb and a thick membrane and, through the blood, the amniotic liquid, the light sometimes shines through. But the revelation reveals nothing but itself, and whatever the secret is, I do not know its language. There is no step forward and no step back.  On some nights I see him looking back at me; watercolors of him, never the whole. He can see me too - how far I’ve come - but not enough. I hope it’s enough to vaporize into hope for him, what we used to call destiny, or the god of broken cobblestones. A few floors below us, Azzurrina sings in forgotten tongue, and a team of researchers is trying, and failing, to record the terror of her chorus, while others, in studying the mystery of the faces, are failing to get to the fundamental fact, which is that my life is happening on the other side of them and I can’t get through. I’ve been very careful with drawing out their map because I’ve stored my memories into another room and, though this little mnemonic trick helps me be wary of them, I do not wish for them stumble into it. I cannot take it, tonight. The documentary will come out on public television either way. The demonic voices must’ve been artificial, in retrospect, and the faces were suspicious smudged. If they had found you back then, put the microphone towards the voice, you would’ve just said you didn’t want to die. Now most of the times the bortyting keeps quiet and I know he’s there only because of the way the light hits his figure, casting a terrible shadow. Some nights I find it’s myself, not him, to be wailing. There’s always a wailing, always a calling - <span class="more_info" title="to make sure that, on the other side, there’s someone listening">alltid ett kall som säkerställer att, på andra sidan, är det någon som lyssnar</span>. In the hours before dawn, as the candle flame dies and darkness in the house becomes perfect, Padre Pio begins to roam the corridors, with boxing gloves covering his stigmata, Mothman takes a dive into air like butter and I can no longer distinguish between the child in the other room, who will manage to survive childhood, and me who’s survived. We both stand with an ear or a mouth to the wall, listening. «Meaningful plenitude»<sup id="fnref:8:1"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup> is denied to both of us. We can’t see what’s happening in the other room - what has or will happen. We make the best of ourselves out of the glimpses we catch, call them hope or a liability, incorporating them into bigger narrative that, with time, we must learn to shed, like snakeskin. We are not allowed complete vision, or complete memory. In this version of the story, we are multiple people, different and distinct, we are two characters across different books connected by legend or prophecy, by theme, not plot. Isn’t there freedom in that, too? It’s the one night of the year, it’s a conjuration. I tell myself it’s getting better. I create a child out of the shadows of him, something I can make sense of, and the difference between imagination and memory gets thinner. He rebels, of course; on nights like this, when the membrane is the thinnest, as past and present merge into the same extended time, I must learn to do right by him, respect the borders of him, how violently they shift, move away from me. But tomorrow the haunted house will be nothing but a house again, and I will have left, bringing with me the haunting, this grief of unbridgeable distance, the vague shape of a future projected on a wall I haven’t looked at in so long.</p> <p>🌹It gets better. We forget the incident. The excitement of it being done also helps. I receive your impressions of the process, archive them inside of me. I share a few of mine, trying not to hurt either of us. Sometimes I do. I’m sorry for it. But we did it. We didn’t give up on this. We land on something different than what I had imagined – something which, over the next months, I will begin to recognize as ours.</p> <p>🌹Researching for this text, I read more about Tove Jansson. I find out that, as many other women of her time, she referred to lesbians, and herself, as “ghosts”. We didn’t watch All of Us Strangers (Haigh, 2023) together; I was looking for a small freedom, a space of feeling unencumbered by anyone else’s presence (I did go with Eesha, but we agreed to sit on opposite sides of the movie hall and reconvene later. After the credits roll, I went to her and cried in her arms for a bit, she let me). It’s also true that I’m not very good at letting you in. <span class="more_info" title="But this is me trying.">Men det här är jag som försöker.</span> Halfway through the movie, Adam stays the night in the impossible house of his parents. When he wakes up from troubled sleep, he’s wearing one of his childhood pajamas, stretched comically, painfully, over his adult body, like a costume. He slips into his parents’ bedroom and talks with his mother about when he used to creep into her bed at night, then of her absence, of the fantasies he had of how they would spend holidays and birthdays together. But here, as the membrane between adult and child becomes the thinnest, the most dangerous, as he is able to find comfort in his parents’ bed again, Adam finds out that all of the grief and terror of that child have made it through, too. A sense of uneasiness grows in the room and, as his father turns into his lover and his mother disappears, blue police car lights flash over the window, the camera moves back to show Adam, brought back completely, physically, to the eleven years old boy he was when his parents died in a car crash. These are the last moments of Adam’s journey into the past, as he manages to access the world of his childhood in an unprecedented way: like in my reading of Stockton, Adam re-inhabites the skin (the clothes, then the body) of the child he was, making memory physical, a space that can be embodied. At the beginning of the movie, Adam lives a monotonous and safe existence, where his past is gathered in a box of photographs and child toys and hidden away under his bed, until a chance encounter with someone he’d like to love acts as a catalyst for the mechanisms of feelings, then memory. Only after Harry, and only because of him, does the membrane of childhood, the only gateway into the world of the children we were, become available for him, and Adam gets to meet his parents again, as both space and time become unreal. Only in confronting their ghosts, in knowing them as an adult (and coming out too), does the continuation of the story, and love, become possible. Like Stockton’s child and Freud’s Nachträglichkeit, the past must be reactivated for it to become available, to be processed, and that is a dangerous and painful process, which, as we see from the first encounter with Harry, has led Adam to avoid feeling, or risking, anything at all. After this night in his parent’s house, Adam wakes up in his own bed and finds shelter from his night’s terror in Harry. He opens up to him for the first time, tells him of the grief of losing his parents, the fear and isolation that came from living in the aftermath of AIDS, moving to the big city, losing friends, finding himself stuck in a life without much pain as well as joy. All of this, he admits, mixed with each other, became the same feeling: «it felt like the future didn’t matter». <span class="more_info" title="Our disagreement over the movie lay in the fact that you read it as a ghost story and a tragedy and I couldn’t.">Vår oenighet om filmen ligger i faktumet om att du, till skillnad från mig, ser den som en tragedi och en spökhistoria och det kunde jag inte.</span> In the finale, Adam has one last lunch with his parents and, this time, they get to say goodbye. Instead of going to his apartment and waiting for Harry to come up, he heads (for the first time) to his place. Opening the door, he finds his lifeless body. Harry, still alive, enters the room and, against Adam’s efforts to spare him the sight, insists on staying, admitting, in between tears, that he can smell his own body, rotting. He must’ve killed himself months before, when, after their first meeting, Adam rejected him. But on this evening, he’s held instead, and convinced to go up, back to Adam’s apartment. In the last scene he hugs him in his bed, as the camera pans away from them, showing cosmic darkness around them, one shining star appearing and swallowing the dark. You, as my brother, saw that as the last moment of happiness granted to them – a strangely Christian-coded visual for the end of a life, for some kind of absolution. But in the scene before, as they find Harry’s body, the body can be identified as his because of its clothes, the same ones that he was wearing during the night of their first encounter. When he enters the room, still alive, Harry is wearing that same salmon sweater and holding the same gin bottle that he failed to share with Adam. Harry becomes double, multiple: he’s not just the one who’s been in a relationship with Adam, he’s also the one who’s been denied his chance at a little warmth, a little company. In that room, the past of his death coexists with the future of his life – a point of conflict in time, in the plot. Adam (aware of the future they had together) stops this past from happening, avoids the fulfillment of a death that feels unavoidable like a prophecy. Throughout the movie, Adam develops a queer ability (or sensibility, if we want to read the movie metaphorically) for getting in contact with the past, for inhabiting the membrane of childhood and re-living and continuing the past: because of this, he becomes able to break the door that separates the past from the present and the future, too. The succession of these two room, where time is folded and unraveled and changed, are an apotheosis of queer time: the refusal of the mortifying rules of reality which determine that we must submit to only one configuration of time and space, that there is only one story for us, that trauma is irredeemable, that we are doomed to repeating it or succumbing to its consequences. As he intervenes to stop Harry from touching his own dead body, as he hugs him to sleep, <span class="more_info" title="Adam is not accepting his death: he’s re-writing history, &lt;i&gt;he’s changing the past&lt;/i&gt;.">Adam accepterar inte sin död, han skriver om historien, han ändrar det förflutna</span>. His engagement with the past has awakened the dead, yes, but also made other configurations of the present possible; coming from an alternative future in which he did have a relationship with Harry, he visits the past of that first night again and is able to change it, to save Harry, to establish a new time. In this way, the tragedy of the broken gay/queer love story is avoided, and gives way to something new, something hopeful. This is what I wanted to say, Konrad. I don’t want us to be ghosts. I want a different story for us. <br/>I’m trying to learn how to read hope, baby.</p> <p>🌹 What I’ve found out about my childhood: <br/> As a child I was not safe. None of us were. I was aware of this and aware that it was wrong to feel like that. Because my heartbreak and my grief could not be held anywhere, because I was required to live in unsafe conditions without any power to change them, I created an ever-growing distance between myself, my body, my feelings. Exposed to these unsafe conditions, I played with the balance between safety and danger, with horror, by scaring myself and others, so as to regain some sense of control, of agency. I tricked myself into believing this distance safety and, after a while, I started calling it home. So much of what happened did so outside of my control. The mask was taken off even as I screamed. I had to watch it happen all throughout my childhood I lived in fear. I feared dawns and beginnings and each and every day and the end of my life. I remember the open door and the way the steps up the stairs sounded and the open room one afternoon then more and the ceiling from my own eyes and that’s enough for now. This child, whether he’s the one I really was or the construction I made, is alive in me and sometimes he screams and sometimes he lashes out at you for what you ask of me, for what you don’t give, for what I don’t know how to ask. &lt;span class=”more_info” title=”I’m trying to tell you that there was a kernel of you in my childhood.”&gt;Jag försöker berätta för dig att det fanns en kärna av dig i min barndom.&lt;/span&gt; I’ve been trying to gather the pieces, to write them together, and I wanted you to have a part as well, because you do. If my memory remains shadowy, exposed to stronger winds that bend it and shape it beyond my will, if the whole category of childhood couldn’t sustain me, couldn’t keep me safe, if all along I tried to escape whatever being a child meant to me, then maybe I never was one. Maybe I am allowed a childhood only now that I am out of the labyrinth. The memories of what hurt are crystallized, safeguarded, and the membrane between me and them is surprisingly clear, though opaque. Awaiting, maybe, «the right to claim a word» I don’t know yet, or knew all along. Maybe I’m learning now. Maybe you teach me. If whatever child I can call is invention, if I cannot penetrate the membrane anyone, if I am doomed to living with the ghost of him, then that means that he’s still there, and I did save him; and if my memory is intangible and changeable, if both queerness and its absence are fictions, if I still cannot write what happened without being so fucking afraid that I will be dismissed, challenged, countered – if there are no facts I can appeal to, if there wasn’t anyone to help me, then I was never inside the reality of the c/Child, and I can take that skin off and write a different story, call it autobiography, memoir, my life. In it, zapping through the afterhour Italian TV channels, I did stumble upon a Mumin cartoon – upon Tofslan och VIfslan, lovers or twins, and Mårran, who didn’t frighten me. In it, my father did really go to Sweden and he brought back something sweet and intangible, a handful of perfect snow, which I picked up from the night stand before I left. If I have no memories I can serve myself with, then I can take the leap and call writing memory, the very thing which saved me. Because if there was once a time in which two of us were kids at the same time, I can record this simple fact in chronological sequence and make it aslant by adding <i>tillsammans</i>. The story, impossible to prove or deny, goes: on one afternoon of primary school, in the courtyard with the tall pine trees, the child you were, your left hand still unscarred, took the hand of the child I was; the affection we discovered in that September of two years ago has not been invented, but rather it moved across history from that one afternoon towards that evening near Viktoria-Luise-Platz, to meet the people we are, who have forgotten but who will remember and tell the story, illuminate childhood with its possibility. And if you were there, in my childhood – then the walls are exploded and it becomes easier for me to believe that there was love, there, and goodness too, and kindness and understanding, that I wasn’t alone with my feelings, that he was there too, and that the punishment of our trespasses didn’t ruin us; and then I remember – this memory which is half writing half shipwreck, pouring out of itself, out of its remembering – I remember that there was play there, too, because despite my malaise, my terminal seriousness, we play now, and it’s nice, it’s just fucking nice, and sometimes we play this game called “fantasy of a house” where I tell you why I sometimes lash out at you and you tell me why you can’t believe my good faith – the missing page to all of this. Konrad, it’s been a long afternoon, a long semester, a rough patch – we booked the tickets, ended the fight – and we are tired of this game, now. <br/> Eventually we go to bed. You turn the light off and, your eyes already closed, you ask me to hug you and I do, just before you fall asleep, before me always. With my head exhausted by the work of the day (the dissatisfaction with the way the words flow, the rare moments in which it becomes easy, the million questions I ask myself daily and dare not answer), I see clearly that, in this little bed, we are moving back in time as well as onward, we are safely grounded in the present, like a sturdy island in a summer storm; then, for the first time in my life, the future opens up like the sea after storm, suddenly infinite and exciting, seen from <span class="more_info" title="this happy little room we write together.">i det lyckliga lilla rum vi skriver tilsammans.</span></p> <p><img src="https://marialaurids.net//assets/blog_posts/posts/meandyou.png" alt="Two children at a dinner table. Multiple glasses in front of them with different heights, some containing water, others with wine. To the left, part of a composition with two big orange flowers and a candle is visibile; next to it, a green water bottle. The child on the left has a checkered powder blue shirt, and is holding what seems to be a piece of bread; his face is playful and looking at the glass of wine that he's reaching out to. The other child has a black romper on a grey shirt and is looking straight into the camera and sticking his tongue out." width="100%" height="80%"/></p> <p>­</p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1"> <p>In the following paragraphs I make more or less free use of Stockton’s essay. Readers of Stockton will find this text to be very different from hers. I want to specify, especially for those who are new to her work, that I do not propose this text as an introduction, explanation or summary of it. It is my own reading which has formed throughout a few semesters of coming back to this it. For example, Stockton never makes a typographical distinction between child/Child; it’s a trick I started using to make sense of her discourse on History, which I do not touch on here. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2"> <p>I borrow this term loosely from Maria Lugones’ essay “Heterosexualism and the Colonial / Modern Gender System” (accessible on JStor at &lt;a href=”https://www.jstor.org/stable/4640051&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;) to mean something like <b>heteronormativity</b>, the belief system that values heterosexuality as good, natural, at the same time the only correct and moral manifestation of human sexuality and the only possible one. I prefer <i>heterosexualist</i> over <i>heteronormative</i> because it puts the accent, like Lugones’ essay, on the pervasive, (made-)invisible, but violent imposition of heterosexuality. This text was my first contact with post-colonial theory and I cannot recommend it enough. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3"> <p>Another term I’ve picked up in Gender theory classes but for whom I don’t have a reference. I don’t know if it’s true, but I have the feeling German academia uses it more than the international/American one. I like it because, like in ‘marginalised’, the <i>-ised</i> suffix makes race a less evident or natural thing that just exists and more of a process that someone is submitted to, at the end of which a racialised subject emerges. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:4"> <p>As a European citizen of Italy and Germany in the second year of Israel’s latest phase of genocide in Gaza and Palestine, I must remark that on all levels, from supplying weapons to participation in propaganda, both of these countries have taken a clear stand on whose children are worth protecting and whose must be annihilated under the pretense of the protection of others. The whole settler colonialist project of Israel has always explicitly seen children as the first threat to its existence and has consistently planned and executed their annihilation. Any discourse which touches on childhood must note that Israel is the greatest threat to world-wide protection of children’s rights and lives. A Free Palestine means freedom from body mutilation, trauma, genocide for the children of Palestine, which means for the children of all of the world. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:5"> <p>Kathryn Bond Stockton, The Queer Child, or Growing Sideways in the Twentieth Century, Duke University Press, 2009, page 6. <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a> <a href="#fnref:5:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p> </li> <li id="fn:6"> <p>I think of the Child, ultimately, as a way to control that phase of human development we call’ childhood’, to channel it towards ‘proper’ growth. This means that it can be understood as a <i>temporal regime</i>, one of those (cultural, economical) systems that regulate the understanding, if not the flow itself, of time. By defining the Child as a second skin, I try to connect these regimes with somatic, bodily experience, in reference to Elizabeth Freeman, who, in “Time Binds”, described the impact of capitalistic, heterosexualist society on our sense of time through the concept of <i>chrononormativity</i>: the regulation of shared, social life with a common sense of time which is created to maximize productivity. This idea of time, both individual and social, is made to appear like «somatic facts» (Time Binds, page 3), that is to say, to appear natural, unquestionable, because it is inscribed, carved into the body and its rhythms/cycles. The Child understood as a second skin is meant to highlight the same point that all temporal regimes are installed and continued by violent and persuasive methods which instrumentalize the body (not unlike heterosexualism and racism). <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:7"> <p>My definition of childhood as membrane, though I imagine it could be effective outside of this discourse too, works mostly in relation to the past and to traumatic events that shape childhood. I want to imagine a future child – a future where a child might be able to define themselves on their own terms, where trauma is avoided with the necessary structures helping them deal with heavily impactful, sudden, complicated events or feelings. I want to imagine that, one day, we will get to the point where children could also create theories of childhood (as they maybe already do, when they are not forgotten, or not listened to). I want all of this specifically for the children of Palestine, Sudan, Congo. On another note, the landscape has changed significantly since I was a child; children, then teens, have a different access to the vocabulary of queerness, even of psychology and trauma, than they did before, even though this argument probably cannot be made global yet. It’s also true that I was a child in Southern Italy, where machismo and all forms of homophobia/misogyny are still rampant. This is to say, I would also like to connect childhood with Muñoz’s theory of utopia, but I cannot access utopian feeling but by this declaration and this short note, because my interest, my need, is in the past, is in the child I was. <a href="#fnref:7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:8"> <p>In my quote-less understanding, essentialism is the understanding of certain human physical or intellectual qualities as natural to certain people: for example, boys are naturally more aggressive and talented in logical thinking, while girls are softer, more scheming, and excel in emotional intelligence (in this case, this is also called biological essentialism, which explains masculinity and femininity as essential characteristics, rooted in biology, in the body, while ignoring the social pressures to conform to ideas of what a boy or a girl is). The same thought process can be applied to queerness: the ‘born this way’ rhetoric, which seems to me a way to justify sexual deviancy by shifting the blame on natural, casual causes, rather than focusing on the reason why there’s a blame at all. By insisting on queer childhood, I do not want to prove I was <i>always</i> queer to justify my queerness of today. If that was the case, I would be content with having been a straight child and developed into a queer adult, or a cis child who would then understand themselves as non-binary. I would rather believe in change rather than fixed, everlasting identity. <a href="#fnref:8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a> <a href="#fnref:8:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="lilla-huset;"/><category term="childhood-theory;"/><category term="all-of-us-strangers;"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mechanisms of love 2</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/mechanisms-of-love-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mechanisms of love 2"/><published>2024-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/mechanisms-of-love-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/mechanisms-of-love-2/"><![CDATA[<p><i>December 2024. Contains spoilers for the movies “Where are you going, habibi?” (Iben), “Weekend” (Haigh), “All of Us Strangers” (Haigh). I sincerely encourage you to watch at least “Weekend” and “All of Us Strangers” before reading this short post or skipping it. They’re absolutely worth the time.</i></p> <p>«I can connect <br/> nothing with nothing.»</p> <p>The first thing I wanted to say is: what is up with two men biking dangerously on the same bike, made just for one? Yesterday was Christmas’ Eve and I had nothing to do so I watched “Where are you going, Habibi?” (Iben, 2015) and found it very charming, despite what the IMDB crowd had to say <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. In this one scene, the two main characters (a gay Turkish guy and an allegedly-straight German guy) are walking side to side, until the German asks the other to hop on. With a little balancing, they bike away gladly, the guest’s legs stretched hazardously in front of him as they speed over Admiralbrücke (and surely part of the reason the movie got to me emotionally was that I could recognize the streets, that I have my own memories attached to the places they visit or pass by). After watching it and being somewhat disappointed with its shortness, I scrolled through the sugguested movies and found “Weekend” (2011), Andrew Haigh’s second movie, who recently directed my beloved “All of Us Strangers” (2023). As I was a little drunk and pleasantly so, I wanted to watch it too – maybe also to compare with the previous ‘bad LGBT’ movie. But the available streaming featured the usual disturbingly unnatural Italian dub, so I waited on the next day and I rented it elsewhere. In it, at some point the two main characters, who might be catching feelings for each other after a one night stand, are taking a walk home, carrying a bike by hand. I was not expecting for one of them to ask the other to join on, but he does, and so on they go, stiff legs, lots of laughs.</p> <p>I was a little surprised to find the same moment in two different movies that, I thought, have nothing in common with each other but gay characters and me, watching them in a row. On second thought, though, more similarities appear: both movies deal with distincly gay moments, and in both of them a looser character who’s more comfortable with his sexuality charms another who’s either completely in the closet or mostly not out. Surprisingly, it is always the more closeted one to offer the uncomfortable bike ride together. So I started thinking: is there something about the bycicle itself which justifies its appereance in two very different ‘gay’ movies, produced for completely different markets? Does the bike work as a metaphor for motor, speeding, direction, loss of it, an instrument made for simple, singular consummation, which gays somewhat explode, twist, turn double, moltiplicate? Does it point to a desire that the more closeted gays have to be silly in public, to be seen together? In “Weekend”, Russel asks Glen to hold himself tight against his chest. They have already fucked at this point but later, when they’re home, Russel shyly refuses Glen’s kisses with a demeanor that, to me, seems to come from shame still, from the fear of having overdone it, of not being able to go back (is this good insight? Is this valuable?). But he invited Glen on the bike, before. For a little while, they were silly togethere, they touched each others’ bodies in public. In “Where are you going, Habibi?”, the supposedly straight guys has the (more) openly gay guy jump in the ‘backseat’, just after the latter said that he’s leaving. What could be the end of their relationships, that hasn’t even really started, is first accelerated by this bike ride that should lead him closer to the embassy, where he will get the papers necessary to leave Berlin, but then seems delayed (the movie’s open ending doesn’t give any real hints as to what will happen) with a long drunken trip to Tempelhof. On the bike again they are visible, bound together, recogniseable. Maybe the two-on-one bike ride is the only way that they compromise visibily, public affection, where for both couples a time limit (most clearly in “Weekend”) has been imposed upon their lives and budding relationships. Maybe the bike ride is an uncomfortable but effective means to expand on this time a little, to open other possibilities without leaving the present, its difficulties. Maybe they’re just boys, and they shroud themselves in boyhood, the common ground between them, and boyish playfulness in order to be close to each other. Or have I just really, really been alone these past days?</p> <p>I really liked “Weekend”. K told me not to watch it because it was sad but I think that’s what I wanted. I saw it with eyes that had already seen and loved “All of Us Strangers”, so I’d been primed to find connections between the two. And there is something to be said about a director who writes two movies with extremely similar situations (in terms of human happenings), but I don’t know what, maybe that that would qualify him as an auteur, whatever that means, an artist with thematic consistency, maybe (is that a desirable quality?) or maybe that there’s a biographical level to be unlocked somewhere, between interviews and other texts by him. But I don’t want to go there, as a form of respect for Haigh too – it’d be far too easy to reduce everything to an autobiographical exercise. There is though an undeniable familiarity to WK after having seen AOUS and maybe someone who watched them in chronological order felt the same about the last one. It’s been tempting for me (in the slow days after the first watch, as I extend the second one, break it into pieces, delay the last fifteen minutes of it) to imagine the second as another attempt at the themes and conflict of the first, maybe even imagining it to be what the other could not be. In order to find that out, I should look at the structures, themes, metaphors – the ‘systems’ of both movies to then discern whether they can be put into that kind of comparistic conversation, to justify the choice. Then, assuming a timeline, I could begin to ask whether Adam and Harry in AOUS manage what Russel and Glen couldn’t in WK – imagine, then realize, a love story that doesn’t bend and break to the rules of time. But the question is biased, I have my reasons for asking it, so, in real academic fashion, I’d probably find the evidence I’m looking for and discard whatever other complication does not serve my purpose, and that is probably the reason that I haven’t continued writing on AOUS, even though I have so much I want to say, because I think it’s a wonderfully complex movie and, without the necessary instruments or frameworks, I am left to my own devices, my own interpretative systems, and they exhaust me.</p> <p>(I’m trying to find a way to write about what I love.)</p> <p>But there are similarities. The shots of the tall building where Russel lives touch directly those of Adam’s isolated house complex; whereas in AOUS Adam repeatedly observes Harry from his window up in the sky and the return of the gaze from Harry signifies the beginning of their relationship, in WK Russell watches Glen walk away from his apartment and he turns away only once, when he has already failed to feign disinterest in him anymore, and one could read the tragedy of the movie already in this scene, because it happens just after the time limit has been established, once the relationship has become impossible. Then, of course, the in-bed scene-s. No bike ride in AOUS, thogh (does the metro count?). I want to believe that it’s not just coincidence, that Haigh was trying to create a line that goes from one to the other, that binds them together, that says something good, something worthwhile about both of them. I’m trying to understand the purpose of this.</p> <p>(Every time they said goodbye I wanted Glen to stay.)</p> <p>There’s a scene of AOUS I couldn’t really make sense of, and not because it’s particularly cryptic, but because I had an instinctive, simple reading of it that I couldn’t do much with. It comes just after Adam has decided to sleep at the house of his parents, when he goes into their bed at night to talk with his mother. His father, wearing a white tank top, makes space for him, then practically disappears from the scene. But when everything turns darker and the police car lights start flashing over the room, Adam turns around in panic and finds that his father has been replaced by Harry. After an initial moment of confusion – seeing his lover where his father was, wearing the same tank top – Adam mutters «You can’t be here.» Not just because he’s in a place which is not meant to exist for him too, but because he’s physically taken up the space of his father, just as he’s taken up the space of himself as a child, signified by the comically small pajamas that he wears. This scene reminded me of the first encounter with the father, where they followed each other around the city outskits with meaningful gazes, mostly in silence, offering each other cigarettes and booze – in a way that reminded me immediately of cruising. This troubling, repeated blending of the line between the familiar/sexual was hard for me to make sense of. It hinted at things that didn’t really make sense in this movie. But “Weekend” offers another interpretation.</p> <p>In the last moments they spend together in bed, their mouth full of sleep (and what a spectacular performance), Glen and Russel experiment with another kind of vulnerability than the one they had the night before, arguing and screaming and fucking. Glen asks Russell why, in the accounts of hookups and relationships he writes, he always focuses on the other person’s coming out. He admits that it’s because he never had one, being an orphan (and already I was thinking of “All of Us Strangers”, because the coming out of Adam to his ghost parents, who died when he was a child, is a focal point in his newfound relationship with them). Glen proposes a game: he’s going to play his father and he’s going to come out. Russel is hesitant, but accepts. There is so much that could’ve gone wrong with this scene – either of them (or the writing) playing this ‘daddy’ acting for laughs, exaggerating it. But it is my favourite scene of the movie precisely because of how it manages to create a moment of absolute sincerity in a fragile moment of (double) acting, just before they must say goodbye to each other. Russel finally gives in and turns sincere and open (with the almost universal languages of coming-outs – the stuttering, the “I don’t like girls” that either follows, as if to excuse its weight, or precedes, to introduce, the hardest thing to say, “I am gay”). Glen looks at him and says that he loves him nonetheless. That touched me deeply already. Then comes the touch of mastery (both from Haigh’s writing and Glen’s actor, Chris New): he adds that «I couldn’t be more proud of you than if you were the first man on the moon». The scene couldv’e collapsced here, fall into cheap comedy, or try to do, say too much. Instead it’s heartfelt, it’s true, and it does something to me (did my parents go beyond the usual, though lucky, declaration of unchanged love? I don’t remember. But I don’t think so).</p> <p>Glen and Russell believe in this moment, they both need to have it and to give it to each other, and they make me believe in it, too. It latches beautifully onto what they didn’t say the evening before in their fight, it gives each of them a new understanding of how the other perceives them. There is a grace here – a sincerity and an affection – that they both extend to the other which I can’t describe. It reminds me of the beautiful lesson of the first part of Bartlett’s “Who was that Man?” and some sections of “The Faggots and their Friends Between Revolutions”: what we can do for each other once we find a space (a time) for us. What grace we can gift, what balsam can we pass over our wounds. If I want to be a little dramatic (and I do), this is the gift that they give each other – this is what makes it easier for them, and for myself, to make some kind of troubled peace with the ending, the closing of their relationship.</p> <p>(What does this second writing, this tracing of the line, accomplish? Am I reminiscing? Am I reliving? Am I bringing anything closer to my heart?)</p> <p>Looking back at AOUS after WK, at the scene in which Harry turns into Adam’s father, I can now find something different in it, I can bring to the surface something which I could always perceive, but remained hidden under the weight of my previous interpretation. The scene doesn’t go as far into the play-out that Russel and Glen indulge in, but it hints at the same fact: the reparative nature of their relationship, what Adam and Harry do for each other. As I’ve argued elsewhere <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, I don’t and cannot see this movie as a tragedy – in my first viewing I already istincly refused to see the ending as the closing off of their relationship after Harry’s ‘suicide’, and with time I found the words to explain that, to me, in the final shots Adam is repairing time, saving the timeline, or creating another, opening up a new time for the both of them, recuparating the past before the moment of loss and avoiding it. This is what Adam does for Harry – more or less literally saving his life. But Harry offers Adam the feeling, the love that prompts his whole journey into the past, at the end of whch he can be saved, too. Harry provides the loving space of care and experience that Adam needs to rebuild his life; he drives him to go out again after his long loneliness, he takes care of him during the drugged-out experience that, somehow, brings him back to his long dead parents’ house, where he stays the night. He gives him love and sex and care – and the way that this happens is also through taking on, at times, the emotional role of a father, through repairing that kind of relationshop for him: whatever that means, it is the same playful but earnest reeancting of family roles that, in “Weekend”, is played out in the coming out scene. Not unlike that, as a matter of fact, the first confession of Adam comes after the night/dream where his father turns into Harry: as he wakes up, he settles down back into reality, into Harry’s care, and he tells him for the first time of how he lost his parents, what shape grief took for him. Adam sees Harry as his father, having melted together into the same body, because the care that is extende to him also means to repair that emotional wound, made from absence and detachment and things gone unsaid, which in turn allows him to patch things up with his actual father. This familiar reanactment is not as strong, not as intentional as in WK, but I think it still expands meaningfully on it.</p> <p>Comparison works here because it sheds light on a moment that would’ve otherwise remained blind in my reading, by which I mean in my understanding of the movie and of my feelings about it. But what is to be gained from the next step I feel tempted towards – proving that Glen and Russels’ story finds its completion, its happy ending, in All of Us Strangers – that its refusal of the rules of reality, its slipping into the tones of fantasy, is a strategy meant to avoid the queer person’s Mr. Melancholy, its sworn enemy (time) by creating a sideways time, a repaired nest where time can be rearranged, stopped, changed? That the two days that are given to Russel and Glen, the only night that Adam and Harry spend together in ‘reality’, are made to explode, to give away into queer time, the rearange of the rules of temporality which makes the happy ending possible? What is it but my well-meaning, childhish desire to make the pain cease, to repair heartbreak over a sad ending?</p> <p>(But in romance, isn’t every sad ending just an editor’s choice – the focus on a moment of a life – won’t there be another love for them, in Nottingham or Portland? Isn’t it possible as well that that they will remain in contact, that Glen will call Russell to admit that his plan is not working, that America was not the new start he had imagined to be, that he must come back home, come back to him? Or won’t they wait the time out, wait in the absence of each other, Russel wearing out the tape of that first mornign together, or never listening to it, and then one day, many lovers past, each deserving their own movie, Glen will show up at the door, or he will be seen up from the window again, and something new can begind?</p> <p>I thought this would help, but it doesn’t. There’s <a href="https://archiveofourown.org/works/search?work_search%5Bquery%5D=&amp;work_search%5Btitle%5D=&amp;work_search%5Bcreators%5D=&amp;work_search%5Brevised_at%5D=&amp;work_search%5Bcomplete%5D=&amp;work_search%5Bcrossover%5D=&amp;work_search%5Bsingle_chapter%5D=0&amp;work_search%5Bword_count%5D=&amp;work_search%5Blanguage_id%5D=&amp;work_search%5Bfandom_names%5D=Weekend+%282011%29&amp;work_search%5Brating_ids%5D=&amp;work_search%5Bcharacter_names%5D=&amp;work_search%5Brelationship_names%5D=&amp;work_search%5Bfreeform_names%5D=&amp;work_search%5Bhits%5D=&amp;work_search%5Bkudos_count%5D=&amp;work_search%5Bcomments_count%5D=&amp;work_search%5Bbookmarks_count%5D=&amp;work_search%5Bsort_column%5D=_score&amp;work_search%5Bsort_direction%5D=desc&amp;commit=Search">seventeen fanfictions</a> about “Weekend” on A03, mostly written by the same three people. Do they get it? What happens if I wrote one, if I read them?)</p> <p>Is this good? Does this make sense? I believe it does – but does it expand on my love? There is so much that is worthy of love, which means, that I love, in all of these films. When I started working on AOUS, immediately after seeing it in March, I watched it twice in cinemas and then planned to do so once more at home, so that I could stop it at my will and complete the chronological notes I had sketched. I wanted to say everything that I could, find meaning into everything, leave nothing unseen. I wanted to love it completely, love it despite its obscurities and flaws, which meant, to light up the obscurities and justify the flaws. I didn’t get very far, of course. I read the book that the movie is vaguely inspired from, made some notes on that, and never managed to watch it a third time. I was trying to be academically rigorous. But I also wanted to do right by the movie, by my love. There was a system, a rule to its story, which if I had understood would have proved my love, solidified it, made me able to write on it and do so intentionally and powerfully, would have set me apart from its other enjoyers, would have proved an unquestionable connection between me and the movie. So why couldn’t I finish it? And why has it taken me this long to get back to these notes, too?</p> <p>(I need to put love to rest, at some point. I need to stop writing, stop thinking about it. Otherwise love – and also the basic fact that a story <i>always ends</i> - could break my heart. I felt this way for “All of Us Strangers”, too, and for “Looking”, that I saw when I was nineteen and again last year, after I found out it was written by Haigh too, in anticipation of AOUS. I’m thinking about watching it again. I thought writing would help, but it’s mostly forgetting.)</p> <p>I took part in a literature analysis contest at my high school when I was eighteen. The trial tests I had taken before and the observations I made in class made it seem somewhat evident (to me) that I’d win. But someone else did and, when the winning text was read, it seemed to me like it wasn’t saying anything good or worthwile about the analyzed poem. It was a formulaic, by-the-books reading, and I decided mine to be better. At some point during the reading I also left, halfway trying to make a scene and also because I couldn’t really contain my tears. I needed this win as a sign that, in my constant struggle against reading, books, intelligence, <i>meaning</i>, I was getting somewhere, I was making progress. Later that day a teacher of mine who had watched over me during the whole process sent me an email. What I remember of it is that she said that the criticism I had expressed before in other attempts was well thought, but it also came from a space of personal resonance, and that the poem that we were required to analyzed for the contest just hadn’t awakened the same in me. She meant to say that I was a passionate student (did she call me a writer?) and not a critic, because a critic’s job is to always find something to say. After this incident, which happened during my last year of high school, I took a break from writing<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>. I didn’t plan an end date to it but it would last for some six months, until I began writing bad but genuine poems in German in Prague. But I thought about this email all along, and I have kept thinking about it in the following years. I’ve been thinking about having a blog since I was sixteen, seeing it as some kind of requirement for the life of a writer, and now that I have one I’m finding it exciting, yes, but also very difficult, and not to find things to talk about (as I feared when I was younger), but to find a way, a methodology, for talking about them. The process always falls in on itself, the drafts pile up, and then I get to moments like these, where I question why I am doing it at all.</p> <p>I don’t want to be a critic. There is so much that is profoundly uninteresting to me or that makes me mad in a way that isn’t enjoyable to write about or to read. At best I am a writer, whch means I’m always autobiographical, if not a little autofictional, and it must not come as a surprise to anyone that anything I write about is ultimately about myself. If I do this well, I’m not just enamored with the sound of my voice or the quest for myself, and all of this can mean something to someone else, too. But I’ve known for a while now that whatever writing means to me, it is connected essentially to my memory and to my love, and I’m trying to understand what the instruments (of fiction, of analysis) I have can ultimately do for my love – for this essential love that I feel for certain films, a little more rarely for books. When I finished watching “Weekend” it seemed natural to me to find a way to write about it somehow, to allow writing to be a continuation of my love. A way to understand the confines of it, its color, to extend it in time, to give myself a chance to feel it before it’s gone. But when I found the bike, this idea of parallels, trying to understand what they do for me or for anyone, weight accumulated on my love, and I couldn’t write anymore. I think I am coming back to this because I want to, because I want to want it and I want to do it, to have done it for myself, because I am trying to extricate the “I want to” from the “I should”; because A. told me to write out of love, if at all, and even if I always knew it, it’s easier when someone tells you.</p> <p>But if I were to compare and contrast the use of the bike in both movies, if I were to create a definition of this unstable affectionate bike ride as a vehicle of expression of homosexuality/homosociality, the only one afforded by the protagonists of these movies, caught in between the desire to express their love and the clawing hands of heteronormativity/straight time, would I get any closer to what I love in them, would I be able to upend my love, make it last a little longer, inform my other days a little more strongly?</p> <p>(The truth is that “Where are you going, Habibi?” was made specifically for me. The white German ‘straight’ guy was of rough but ultimately tender kind I’ve dreamed about often when I was younger and closeted, and there’s a boyish beauty to the other one which is extremely striking to me, a certain cleanlines, in the sense of directness, to his face which made me develop that sort of romantic attention that I am certainly not new to. In one scene, he is meant to play the human lamp in a stage rehearsal led by his uncle, which translates to him wearing a lamp head over his and a house robe, for some reason. Two actors come up to him and the boy among them takes the lamp off, unveiling the Turkish’s guy face stretched into an exaggerated smile. The other guy just stands there, clearly taken aback by his beauty, that is strangely so evident in that moment, and I felt the same. What can I do about this but forget – or try this small recap, a writerly exercise by which I run my fingers over his face and type over it some words to describe his beauty, make it mine? What can I do to make this feeling part of the mechanisms of my mind?)</p> <p>I’ve read reviews arguing that “Habibi” doesn’t go anywhere, that it’s too fast or too slow, and that’s all true somehow. Part of me wishes that I could write something more elegant, more detached, to change their minds, to clean the slate of the film. I wish I could tell them that the last scene, where the straight? and the gay guy are running around Tempelhof, getting drunk and almost totally naked, was very sweet to me. That it reminded me of my adolescence, of the nameless desire I had then which has remained nameless today, sated temporarily by the straight boys I had short-lasting but intense friendshops with that always lapped on the sentimental, the romantic. That sometimes running around at night and being a fool with your straight best friend is all you can have. That sometimes it’s what you want, too, that sometimes, many years later, you wonder if that was what you really needed, what your heart wanted. But autobiography is a defunct genre now, autobiographical feeling always entails something suspicious, and people are very quick to dismiss it today.</p> <p>In bringing these two movies together, they begin to form a memory, a hard core that I hope I will not forget. The sense of these days (these weeks alone, the passing of Christmas, a few of those numb days before New Year’s eve) coagulate around it. I still do not know what criticims, or writing in general, can do for my love. And it’s not even criticism – just sustained, more or less rigorous thinking. It’s not academia. It’s not pure writing because that’d be fan-fiction, which, in its pure form, I haven’t really tried. It’s an essay in the sense of an attempt. Zine writing, maybe. A blog post.</p> <p>Same as when I was a child, I do not know what to make of my love. But it must go somewhere. It must.</p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1"> <p>Two reviews in particular are worthy of contempt: <a href="https://www.imdb.com/review/rw7421525/?ref_=rw_urv">this one</a> who argues that the movie is good only for “gay movie standards”, which is ludicrous because objectively speaking it must one of the worst ‘LGBT’ movies I’ve seen, and <a href="https://www.imdb.com/review/rw3697702/?ref_=rw_urv">this other</a> who, in 2017, argued that racism has been solved in Germany and the movie’s portrayal of it is unfair. I couldn’t help but wonder, why are are all people called Horst assholes? <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2"> <p>(Pompous bastard.) <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3"> <p>RIlke and his letters to a young poet are also, if not mostly, to blame. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mechanisms-of-love;"/><category term="a-nameless-desire;"/><category term="all-of-us-strangers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[December 2024. Contains spoilers for the movies “Where are you going, habibi?” (Iben), “Weekend” (Haigh), “All of Us Strangers” (Haigh). I sincerely encourage you to watch at least “Weekend” and “All of Us Strangers” before reading this short post or skipping it. They’re absolutely worth the time.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">barndomsfragment 1 (lilla huset part I)</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/konrad1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="barndomsfragment 1 (lilla huset part I)"/><published>2024-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/konrad1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/konrad1/"><![CDATA[<style type="text/css">.more_info{border-bottom:1px dotted;position:relative}.more_info .title{position:absolute;top:20px;background:#f5b49d;color:#3e3f47;text-align:center;padding:6px;left:0}</style> <p><i>With and for Konrad Karlsson.</i> May-December 2024.</p> <p><br/> <img src="https://marialaurids.net/assets/blog_posts/posts/Screenshot 2024-05-27 113548.png" alt="A zoomed-in screenshot of a picture on a computer, showing a child with a confused look on his face. The picture is too zoomed-in to distinuish any real details of the place." width="100%" height="100%"/></p> <p><i>25 ‎May ‎2024, ‏‎12:37:</i></p> <p><i><span class="more_info" title="You never told me about Troll in the Wings.">Du berättade aldrig om Troll i kulisserna för mig. </span> I found out about it last year, in one of those August afternoons I spent lazily browsing on my computer while you worked in the other room. The play, the second official Mumin theatre adaptation written by Tove Jansson and directed by Vivica Bandler, is known today mostly because of its beginning, in which the Mumin actors enter the stage with usual, intact costumes to then remove their fluffy heads – unmasking, amongst others, the perfectly childish smirk of Lasse Pöysti, playing Moomintrollet. This was ostensibly done to give the actors more freedom with voice and facial expressions, but a dark-internet myth has gathered around the play: children in the audience terrorized by this quasi Mumin decapitation, revealing horribly out-of-place humans inside their white, rotund bodies. With the following performances and the TV broadcast the incident was repeated, making the play into a uniting traumatic memory for generations of Swedish children.</i></p> <p> When I started writing this in May, I wanted to talk about childhood – mine and yours, or rather, the projection of mine on yours, because you don’t like talking about the past and I try to respect that. In the following months, with the following rewrites, I set out to find more information on this play. I was hoping to see the taking-off of the masks – to hear, if not see, the children’s reaction – but I haven’t been able to find any clips of it. In the (unofficial) Mumin wiki, which my research history states I consulted, this ‘decapitation’ is mentioned without any horrific undernotes. Were children really scared? Where did I get the idea that they were? I can't find any other hint in my web search chronology or online. While the absence of proof solidifies the status of the event as a myth, there must’ve been another source, expanding on the story to prove, once more, the Internet’s strange passion for finding the grotesque, the uncanny, the not-quite-right, the traumatising in children’s stories. And that I hadn’t just invented it. </p> <p> You have, of course, no memory of Troll I kulisserna. You were born too late; the Mumin stories you grew up with were different, safe, an uncomplicated background: there, but never essential. <span class="more_info" title="But were there other stories of horror that captured you, when you were young?">Med fanns det någon annan marginell skräck från sagor som fängslade dig när du var liten?</span> You became uneasy when, during one of my marathons, I showed you the ’70 Mumin episode in which Mårran appears for the first time. After asking me to press stop, you told me of how deeply unsettling it was, as a child, to see her towering over Sniff; mysterious, cold, silent. A creature one couldn’t make sense of, couldn’t speak to. Did you have to distinguish, then, between what your eyes just saw and the child’s memory, enlarged, made stranger against the backdrop of your mind?</p> <p> Whether I came up with it or someone else, the question is: what feelings, fake or real, were activated and subsumed into the memory of the Mumin beheading as it was passed on, shared, confused, installed in the precarious architecture of recollection - which <span class="more_info" title="pleasures and terrors">«njutningar och fasor»</span>, otherwise unspeakable, found their expression in it?</p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 I was gifted the complete edition <span class="more_info" title="in translation">(översatt)</span> of the original Tove Jansson Mumin strips for my eighteenth birthday, long before I met you. I was only a little into them, mostly fascinated by Snufkin, but it was the gift of a friend trying to share her passion for them with me. When I told you, did you feel that I was being ungenuine, maybe inventing, doing too much - or that I was trying to steal from the cultural depository of your childhood? Is this how you felt about the latest 3D animated series, made for an international audience with puzzling British accents, that also moved me?</p> <p>Or did you just not care - had it been that long?</p> <p><span class="more_info" title="But you gifted me a Snufkin cup for my birthday last year.">Ändå gav du mig en Snusmumriken-kopp i födelsedagspresent förra året.</span> Were you letting me in on the secret, your childhood, the one thing we cannot share, no matter how much I’d like to - were you welcoming me into it or just indulging me and my childish desires?</p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 <span class="more_info" title="I don’t remember my childhood and that’s one of the few things I can say with certainty about it.">Jag minns inte mycket från min barndom, och det är en de få saker jag kan säga med säkerhet.</span> Another one: you weren’t there. But then again, I wasn’t either. And not just in the sense that I, the person I’ve come to be, do not and cannot live there anymore - the basic fact that the membrane of childhood doesn’t allow trespassing: «my infancy is long dead and I am alive»[^1] ; but because I barely lived in that house, consumed by the business of survival, which makes ghosts of us all. My memory, the second house, made into a broken sieve, unfit for my purposes, the tasks of life.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 I look through my notes, I look back. But I find nothing - neither proof that someone else did write about Troll i kulisserna's traumatic past, nor that I, for some reason, invented it. Reading this again, I think: if the Internet had been as it was ten, fifteen years ago - could I have started something? Do you think that someone would’ve believed me? Troll i kulisserna could’ve been one of those stories in which Internet subculture, with its inclination towards morbidity, interacts with the loose fabric of memory, which is all the looser in childhood, remaining malleable, mobile, decades after its imprinting.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 Writing about myself is easy, as long as nobody sees. Writing about us is hard. I’m looking for a frame for us, a crowd for this room. Generations of queers have gathered in private places[^2], celebrating newborn tongues and attending to the wounds of the first years, when everything passes through the skin, that unfit membrane. When we met I went in headfirst because I felt that you could take it, that you wanted to - <span class="more_info" title="and I hope you felt the same">och jag hoppas att du kände likadant.</span> I felt myself falling in love with you (clearly, secretly) when you sat on my bed and told me of the child you were, of the story behind the scar on your left hand. I wanted to pick it up and kiss it; I don’t remember if I did. We had known each other for less than two weeks. Somewhere on your phone you have a screen recording archiving our first chats and witnessing a miraculous fact: that, in that often crude place where we met, the first pictures we sent each other were of the seas of our hometowns. There, amidst the yellow and the black, I saw the shores of Gotland and thought: I’d like to go there. Then: I think he gets it; «… <span class="more_info" title="the one pain / which is inconsolable">den smärta / som är så otröstlig</span>, the loss of one’s shore …»[^3] </p> <p><span class="more_info" title="Was it easy to receive the story of my childhood?">Var det enkelt att höra om min barndom?</span> In the beginning I wanted to tell you of the places I had escaped so that I could come to this city, where I would meet you. I wanted to put everything in sequence and see what meaning would come from it. What role you could play. Now this retroactive act is necessary to both of us, because it explains me, my resistances to you. In truth - only in telling does the pain become evident, and I can begin. Unlike Augustine, I have no God to call to, no omniscient eternal perspective to allow the retrieval of childhood under the image of eternity, the beginning act of the Western autobiography. I do not know where to begin. I need another context, an excuse - a song, a movie, a book. <span class="more_info" title="You, listening.">Du, som lyssnar.</span></p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 I’m reading about queer memory. It’s shaping up to be a weird semester: pausing uni, trying to get therapy, writing about something new, somewhat more, somehow always less. After a few months of not approaching theory, I started reading Castiglia and Reed’s sad and exciting essay, <i>If Memory Serves</i>, on the effects of remembering and (institutional, collective) forgetting in the aftermath of AIDS. I think I need to go to the roots - of queer temporalities, of queer theories, of us, somehow, because we all exist in a world irrevocably shaped by it. <span class="more_info" title="I’m trying to learn. I’m trying to remember.">Jag försöker lära mig. Jag försöker förstå.</span></p> <p>I’ve always known that my personal memory was tattered and broken; I am starting to see that I never accessed a social, generational one as well. I have been severed not just from myself, but from an entire history of queerness - of Italian queer and trans activists (Porpora Marcasciano, Mario Mieli) who created the space in which I could’ve found rest and solace, had I dared to. But I couldn’t. The business of survival cut what remained of the thread of memory, it required me to disconnect from myself and the stories before and around me. When I walked to my high school or across the tiny streets that suddenly give way into big squares and churches in Naples, when my father drove me back home late at night, I looked away from the trans women strutting by. Was that survival again? Wasn’t that immediate fear which struck at the sight of them the beginning of this betrayal to myself, my history? This happened much later, when I wasn’t a child anymore. But I always knew where to look and, most importantly, where not to. And how can I draw a clear line between the child and the teen, when that child never died and was never really there and I live in the long aftermath of him, too?</p> <p>(I can’t say what was that severed. I can’t say yet.)</p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 Maybe I did invent this story about Troll i kulisserna in those anguishing days of August, as I crashed at your place because my housing contract was done and I couldn’t find anything else, when our patience for each other was so thin and so much damage was done.</p> <p>In trying to make sense of this, I realize that what I find so fascinating about this mishap is its shift in logic. Although the removal of the Mumin masks has a practical explanation, that moment can be read also as revealing a raw materiality in the otherwise intact body of the Mumin. The consequences, which are immediately understood by children, are: their soft skin can be taken off; their fluffy bodies can be emptied out and inhabited by something different; this, of course, if it wasn’t a costume, a decoy, all along. This revelation raises a morbid question: what is a Mumin, actually? Is it an animal that can be killed and whose hide can be worn - or a strategy of prey? Who hides, then, in their big, friendly bodies? Why is Lasse Pöysti’s smile so unsettling? <span class="more_info" title="Danger in Moominvalley">Fora i Mumindalen - the safest of places</span>. Through this logic, the familiar and inconspicuous bodies of Muminpappa and Muminmamma become <span class="more_info" title="a skin - a membrane">en hud - ett membran</span>, as changeable as memory itself, the unstable resource for this story: mine, unable to find my sources anymore, and that of those children who, writing about it online, would’ve re-membered the event years after its passing, bringing that fear back to themselves; not unlike you, unable to stand the sight of Mårran.</p> <p>🌹 In that same August, you picked out a dub of the original 1969 Mumin anime with the original finlandssvenska accent for me, the one you grew up next to. My childhood didn’t have an accent. We watched Italian dubs of anime with the pedantic, impersonal Italian that doesn’t really belong anywhere. It was the first hint that there is not such a thing as Italy, but I wouldn’t get it until, in Berlin, I noticed that my longing called for the seas of my hometowns, Napoli och Pozzuoli, not for whatever sea touches the nation. I was ashamed of liking these shows publicly because of the kinship they inspired - Dragonball with the rowdy boy friends of my childhood, Marmalade Boy with the girls I had fragile and tentative friendships with. (I’m older now and I’m trying not to be ashamed of what I like. I bought myself a green fleece pälsmössa-like hat with a Snufkin design for my birthday; when things got dark in August, I watched the Mumin anime you had shown me - three, four episodes in a row, at times.) </p> <p>Talking about Astrid Lindgren and Tove Jansson at our first dinner, your mother got teary-eyed. My father, too, would get emotional about the Carlo Collodi stories he read as a boy. When I approached those heavy hardbacks, with their distinctly old design with a suspicious interest in order, I found them too Christian, too moralising, the language too old, too distant. My childhood, the real one, the one that came and went, wasn’t sustained by any Italian narration of childhood. The entrusting of stories from one generation to the next didn’t happen for me in the same way it did for you and maybe that’s why I latched on to yours so strongly - so strangely, so backwardly, years before I met you. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹Sometimes, out of nowhere, I get worried that your birthday passed and I didn’t get you anything. But I wrote you a letter. I always forget I did. I won’t repeat what it said, but I did tell you that writing a letter to you was a way to let you into this place, the only home I have; to solidify your place in the architecture of my mind, to make you part of the energy that sustains me. I sometimes think, out of the blue: there’s a queer future ahead of us. Whatever that means, it begins with a paragraph which features us both, under the rubric of an unlikely ‘us’. I know it exists because I will it - I write it. </p> <p>But for this to work, I have to trust you. <span class="more_info" title=" I have to entrust myself - my voice - to you.">Jag måste lita på mig själv - min röst – till dig.</span></p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹<span class="more_info" title=" Growing up, my father used to tell me of the time that, when he was young and on his pilgrimage to the North Pole, he stopped in Sweden. ">Under min uppväxt brukade min pappa berätta om den gången han var ung och stannade till i Sverige under sin pilgrimsfärd till Nordpolen.</span> He told me people got naked as often as possible, were very sexually open and every meal was served with jam and milk. This, as well as a few other hints like IKEA names and midsummar poles, was the context I evoked to make sense of you. But when I told you, you just laughed and said my father must’ve been somewhere else. It hurt me a bit to hear. I still repeated this anecdote over the second dinner with your parents, to be conversational and pleasant. I thought of my parents then - what language they would use to talk with you. The bravado that my father would summon to put together the very few English words he knows with whatever linguistic souvenirs of this mythological trip he could resurrect, in the spirit of that specifically Neapolitan brand of arrogance, the unfounded belief that, with their hand dialect and scraps of English, they can make themselves understood across any linguistic divide. I have no idea what my mother would do. She would probably ask me to translate, or count on her grimaces, kept alive by working with children, to communicate with you. But I won’t allow for the three of you to sit at that kitchen table; the pictures that my father took of this alleged Sweden rest somewhere in his nightstand, and I remember taking another look at them before I left - proof that, even shortly, one of us could leave. Two years ago, I asked him to send some of them to me. <span class="more_info" title=" That was the necessary prologue to me telling them about you. ">Det var den nödvändiga uppbyggnad som behövdes för att jag skulle berätta om dig för dem. </span> But he forgot, I didn’t press him, and then I stopped answering the phone when he called. Trying my hardest to make something different of my tongue, to twist it in different sounds. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹A memory is a chance and a liability. Allowing it invites pain in and pain always brings you back to yourself, the small confines of your body, and for the longest time I couldn’t be in that room, because it was the least safe. I’m learning how to be there - how to just be. To overcome the haunting, make the space habitable. <span class="more_info" title=" To have a spare bed, when you come over. ">Att ha en extrasäng till dig när du sover över. </span> </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 Then finally I figure it out. </p> <p>Looking at the Mumin wiki again for answers, I find this passage, ignored until now: <i>The same practice would return to great controversy in the 1969 show.</i> I follow the hint and it all begins to make sense. In the 1969 TV broadcast series “Mumintrollet”, a king gets hay fever by looking at the Mumin through a telescope, and orders for their snouts to be removed. While in the first episode they move (quite goofily) across the Muminhuset in their usual costumes, in the second episode a secondary character keeps Mumintrollet tied down after having tied his head to the door knob, so that when Muminpappa enter the room, the camera shows his head flying towards him. Again Lasse Pöysti’s face appears underneath, visibly shocked, touching his eyes and face, lamenting the loss of his <i>näsa.</i></p> <p>This is, somehow, much worse than what I had thought - the closest we can get to a real decapitation in a Mumin story. As I had to make peace with the idea that I came up with the story, I am shocked at how closely what I wrote about it resembles the actual show, which I had not seen before. The web results for ‘Mumintrollet 1969’, though scarce, report on screaming children, making it mandatory, for all following theatre and TV adaptations, that the Mumin wear their heads and never, never again reveal the actors hiding in their bodies.</p> <p>Does this answer everything? Can I close this chapter, now? </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹At the first dinner with your parents, as you and your father got busy talking and switched to your tongue, I leaned in towards your mother and showed her the picture of Tove Jannson I have saved on my phone. In it, she swims blissfully in the water before her sanctuary in Klovrahun: immensely beautiful and serene, balancing a flower crown on her head. The water looks deep but she’s smiling. I’ve had it saved for years, I told her. </p> <p>I showed this to her to demonstrate the extent and the duration of my devotion, to retrace the same connection which, at the next dinner, a few months later, I would highlight with the unfaithful tale of my father’s trip. <span class="more_info" title=" I showed it to her as a talisman, knowing she’d understand its power, something both reminiscence and prophecy, to try to tell her that I understand, that I’m trying to understand. "> Jag visade den till henne som en slags talisman, Medveten om att hon förstår dess kraft. Både ett minne och en profetia. Att försöka få henne att förstå att jag förstår, att jag försöker förstå. </span></p> <p>And that I’ll take care of you. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹I think of you, as a baby, left outside in the Gotlandic winter to get acclimated to the cold. I don’t center my doubts that it works or even the curious, sudden memory that, as a child, I was always cold. I imagine you moving your tiny hands in the stroller, losing your soft gaze from snowflake to snowflake, falling in slow unending time. Everything moves quietly and you are not afraid; <span class="more_info" title=" you never cry. ">du gråter aldrig. </span></p> <p>No image of my childhood, real or fabricated, trasmits me this much peace. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹When I first met you, I had the feeling I knew you already. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹I want us to meet here, in this imperfection - the mess of history and timelines, us trying to make sense of it, to put the words one after the other and balance our respective powers over language. My words, your tongue. My time and your time. <span class="more_info" title=" But I trust you.">Men jag litar på dig. </span> I’m deciding to trust you. I trust that you’ll take care of me. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹<span class="more_info" title=" Time is at the heart of what I write. I guess it’s because, in a way, I’m always trying to go back. And the more I write, the more the old paradigm collapses: linear time and straight time, the lie that all of it points towards an absolution which, if we’re honest, will not see; that where and who you’ve been are different than the places you’ll move to and the people you will meet and become similar to. The more I become aware of this, the easier it gets for me to imagine that, maybe, forgiveness is here already, that nobody will save us and that everything is anointed; the clearer I see that the lines which extend from where I stand, anchoring themselves into the future and making waste of the past, are straight and monodirectional, that I haven’t placed them myself, that they cannot describe me or anyone I love; because the lines are actually all jumbled up, and you won’t believe where they end;">Tiden är kärnan i det jag skriver. Jag antar att det är för att jag, på ett sätt, alltid försöker gå tillbaka. Ju mer jag skriver, destå mer kollapsar den gamla paradigmen; linjär tid och rak tid, lögnen om att allting pekar mot något syndaförlåtande vilket, om vi skall vara ärliga, vi inte kommer kunna se; att vart och vem du varit är annorlunda än platserna som du flyttar till och människorna du kommer träffa och bli mer lik. Ju mer medveten jag blir om det, destå lättare blir det att tänka mig att förlåtelsen är här redan, att ingen kommer att rädda oss och att allting är smord. Destå klarare ser jag linjerna som sträcker sig från där jag står, som ankrat fast sig i framtiden och som struntar i det förflutna, att dom är raka och enspåriga. att jag inte placerat dom än, att dom inte kan beskriva mig eller någon jag älskar; för att linjerna är egentligen huller om buller, och du kommer inte tro vart dom slutar:</span> because the past and the future are actually communicating vases, if you dare, and the present is more than just the place between them; because time is a road with multiple lanes and the atom crashes that ensue are those moments of wonderful clarity when you stop and think about the trajectories, the absolute causality and necessity of everything - <span class="more_info" title="those days of early summer, the first call of spring… "> de första dagarna av försommar, det första vårropet...</span></p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹Do you see what I mean? </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹I’m sorry I haven’t learnt Swedish yet, baby. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹There’s a story I’ve been thinking about for a while. I never wrote down even a word for it, except for a note, titled “Mumin X Kafka”, which dates back to my last birthday. <span class="more_info" title=" Here it goes. ">Här kommer den. </span> A guy wakes up from restless dreams to find himself turned into a Mumintroll. As he looks down on his body, he finds it particularly white and soft, with a new, distinctive roundness, so he gets up to look for the mirror. In it, he finds big Mumin eyes staring back at him from a big, white Mumin head. The change is registered with a mixture of glee and terror, and the new Mumin falls back on his bed, unable to go on with his day. </p> <p>It’s the details that are hard to get down in this story - why glee, why terror? Then, is there a job the man has to attend to? Will he call in sick or commute in this new body, will it get dirty with the city’s smog? Where does this person’s consciousness reside - what crawlspace between body and mind? Which ultimately means: <span class="more_info" title=" what’s the real difference between being in a Mumin body or in a Mumin costume, when you’re not one?">vad är den egentliga skillnaden mellan känslan av att vara i en muminkropp eller i en muminkostym, när du inte är en? </span> Again, <i>just what is a Mumin?</i> I wanted it to be a story about this: finding out what it means to be a Mumin in a non-Mumin world, being exiled from Mumindalen, never having been there. </p> <p>I never wrote it down because, even stealing the tone and effect of the Metamorphosis, I couldn’t figure out a disguise effective enough to hide the obvious fact that it was a story about waking up in your childhood bed and not being the child you once were. </p> <p> <span class="more_info" title="In the last scene, the new Mumintrollet, having found his courage, leaves his room and takes off his Mumin head to confront his father, smoking in the kitchen, in the last hour before sunrise.">I sista scenen så har det nya mumintrollet, som hittat sitt mod, lämnat sitt rum och tagit av sitt muminhuvud för att konfrontera sin far, rökandes i köket, sista timmen innan soluppgång.</span></p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹Which words belong to whom, now? Are you stumbling over mine, will you ask me what I mean? What’s happening to my word choice, my weird English? Which words are you using - what do they remind you of, who did you speak them with? What past comes back to you now, as we mix on the page, as we spill, as we speak? </p> <p>In the world of conversations outside of here, I try to reply to your worries: it’s not about my words anymore, but ours; not my point of view, but yours - not about fidelity, or accuracy, but what happens when you bring me into your language, that house of yours I can’t access. It’s about what gets lost, yes - but also about what you can add, what and whose hands hold us, now, as we speak together. Your family, the ghost of mine, forbidding me my hometown, the tongue I thought safe. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹Two years ago, when I read Stockton’s essay for the first time, <span class="more_info" title=" I asked you if you were a queer child.">en gång frågade jag om du som barn var queer. </span> I forgot your answer, but it was just the beginning, fragile and necessary. More follow: how did you think of yourself? What words did you use to describe yourself? I know you don’t want to tell. I ask you to listen, then. <span class="more_info" title=" It’s much easier to talk, when I know you’re listening.">Det är så mycket lättare att prata, när jag vet att du lyssnar. </span></p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹<span class="more_info" title=" Through the story of your childhood, I get closer to mine.">Genom historien om din barndom, kommer jag närmare min.</span></p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 I did not invent this story about Troll i kulisserna.</p> <p>But I still fabricated around it, mixing plays together, the effect of one on the other. <i>Why</i> did I do that, <i>why</i> did I feel compelled to imagine terror and locate it in childhood?</p> <p>Why can't I remember anything, not even this? Why has Troll i kulisserna, this story between memory and imagination, ingrained itself into my mind like a secondary memory, vivid though unreal - a distant relic of a childhood that wasn't mine, not even yours, but running alongside, sideways, to the one I had?</p> <p>Silence echoes from the other side of the membrane. Changing memories, changeling child.</p> <p><br/> <br/></p> <p><i>Second part available <a href="https://marialaurids.net/blog/2025/konrad2/">here</a>.</i></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="lilla-huset;"/><category term="childhood-theory;"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">after the exhibition</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/aftertheexhibition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="after the exhibition"/><published>2024-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/aftertheexhibition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/aftertheexhibition/"><![CDATA[<style>img{float:left;border:0 dotted black;margin:0 20px 0 5px}body{text-alignment:justified</style> <p><i>October 2023_September 2024.</i></p> <p>What came back to me after I read his story out loud, overwhelmed with emotion, or later coagulated around it:</p> <ul> <img src="https://marialaurids.net/assets/blog_posts/posts/aftertheexhibition.jpeg.jpg" alt="A space aside inside of a partly lit underground garage. The space is enveloped by curtains with white and blue hues." width="50%" height="50%"/> <li>I feel that loving writing is constantly failing at the thing you love.</li> <li>The magic of us, what we can do together.</li> <li>Prague in February, when I was alone but I knew that someone was waiting for me back in Berlin, in the room where the apple tree that Steve gave me will, surprisingly, survive a whole winter, a bit of spring too. The last months before leaving home: all of its beauty and terror, the long hours of preparations, the time carved away for my friends. The last week, singing at the night with I., the hours at the bar, which advanced slowly; the month I lived with B. and I felt the pull to stay, to move in a little closer. Beginning of an October past, when F. came to visit and we walked along the same life for a little while again. The morning I’ll arrive in Paris, battered and confused, and S. will pick me up from the station and organize a huge breakfast that will go on for hours; days later, when I’ll smoke with F. on the balcony and try to explain the kind of life I’m preparing, what still scares me. What came out of the exhibition – it will be too early for this, and I will fail, again.</li> <li>The sunlit evenings of the first lockdown, when I forced myself to write every night and something came out of that, too, even if it didn’t have to. </li> <li>The night out when me and Coco rejoiced over learning that we had used the same word to describe the particular electricity of the exhibition, <i>magic</i>. Not an uncommon word, maybe not one a writer should use proudly. But I was drunk and sentimental that evening and I must protect that feeling, too: the wonder of having carved the same word to describe the same time - a tautology of magic, inspiring, confirming itself.</li> <li>Writing the first draft of this and trying (without success) to define a difference between remembering and reminiscing.</li> <li>I’ve interlaced my heart with yours. Doesn’t matter for how long. Ribbons of yours are woven in with mine. Traces; I hope you feel the same. </li> <li>Thinking a lot about memory, my hometowns. In the first year in Berlin I missed the sea the most and I tried to make the first image of my previous life out of it – gathering lines of poems, pictures real and imagined, the words of friends, too, born by the sea, to make a figure of my own. All along the sea was there, unchanged, with the after-image of me and my brother staring out into it before he left. Me, wondering when meaning would kick into place, fill in the experience. I remember the narrow, internal streets of Pozzuoli – the ample ones of Naples, opening (with a gasp) towards a sudden sky, the sea. What does missing mean? It’s only the heart adjusting. In my first months, I lied to it and let myself reminisce, promising to come back, until it didn’t matter anymore. Corners of Berlin make me cry, now. Every time I walk along Potsdamer Strasse I think of you, of us. The time me and Agata walked three or four bus stations from the Kunstraum and talked about twins and doubles of many kinds and it was sweet to have someone to speak in Italian with.</li> <li>I’ve tried to talk to each of them about the specific shape of this magic. This is what I’ve landed on: the magic was the magic. <i>You should’ve been there</i>. This magic was the magic of us. Of our time: the days of our meeting, the few months we shared, that sacred week before the opening. This magic was the magic of us, doing the thing we love. The magic was us and emanated all around from us and it came and went in waves, because pure feeling is unsustainable, but never went away. I remember blue make-up powder being put in a old salad bowl and then shared. The kitchen, our retreat, which Richie’s costumes made into a backstage, a theatre of its own. Then we went into the exhibition. </li> <li>You must develop a technique. Then you must develop another. You must have a method for summoning and you must not abuse it. You must learn how to distinguish between what must be summoned and what suffices to be recalled or imagined. Don’t call what doesn’t need to called. <i>Dream new dreams</i>. </li> <li>The magic reached its peak in two moments: when I read Tommaso’s words for the second time, after Véra instructed me on how to gather my words. Then, afterwards, when we hosted the second guided tours for strangers who would, in one day, see three or four exhibitions, who knows how many labours of love. We guided them and I felt like, for how much we tried, for how much they wanted to, they’d never be part of the magic, because it belonged to us, it emerged from these months of contact, the daily company in the week of the installation. And I felt we were like children of the same kind, strange and aslant, swimming around in a tight pack, in and out of the swarming schools of strangers, as we hyped up those for whom the time had come to explain their work (with words reasonable and intimate enough), until the moment was over, the light moved to the next piece and we reabsorbed into our group to be congratulated and held. Always a good word, always a work of love. We all hugged in front of Eze's glass trinkets, reflecting complex lights, or maybe not at all.</li> <li>When I called Mattia the last morning of the installation because nothing worked and I was ashamed of being so unprofessional and in the same room with you all he calmed me down and promised me <i>we</i>’d find a way. Mascha helped me put up the pages, stayed with me, patient and with unshakable faith in the success of our endeavour. </li> <li>The last day, before we had to leave, I went and sat down in Lu and Coco’s embryonal space. I closed my eyes, I let the sounds of water and whispers align my breath into a kinder rhythm. I made space for memory, for being there. </li> <li>I knew that something in my heart had shifted (like an old cosmic mechanism commanding the eclipse and the seasons of the moon) as I read the last words of Tommaso. I knew then that, despite my imprecisions, my rushing, my shortcomings, the slips of my pen and my mouth, despite myself, that Tommaso is alive, that he had made it through, that the ritual had been successful.</li> <li>I realized last week, getting sentimental again with Lula, that I’m not done talking about this. I don’t want to exhaust the magic, to say it all. </li> <li>Happiness is honey dripping into the heart. I move around our group like a zealot (in the blue coat Jean-Noël said made me look like a gay wizard), I want to know of everyone, I need everyone of us to know; then I step out of our swarm to see my friends, my boyfriend, to send messages to the absent and the unwilling, because I need to tell everyone that the magic was happiness and I found out that happiness gifts time back.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="queer-things-take-time"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[October 2023_September 2024. What came back to me after I read his story out loud, overwhelmed with emotion, or later coagulated around it: I feel that loving writing is constantly failing at the thing you love. The magic of us, what we can do together. Prague in February, when I was alone but I knew that someone was waiting for me back in Berlin, in the room where the apple tree that Steve gave me will, surprisingly, survive a whole winter, a bit of spring too. The last months before leaving home: all of its beauty and terror, the long hours of preparations, the time carved away for my friends. The last week, singing at the night with I., the hours at the bar, which advanced slowly; the month I lived with B. and I felt the pull to stay, to move in a little closer. Beginning of an October past, when F. came to visit and we walked along the same life for a little while again. The morning I’ll arrive in Paris, battered and confused, and S. will pick me up from the station and organize a huge breakfast that will go on for hours; days later, when I’ll smoke with F. on the balcony and try to explain the kind of life I’m preparing, what still scares me. What came out of the exhibition – it will be too early for this, and I will fail, again. The sunlit evenings of the first lockdown, when I forced myself to write every night and something came out of that, too, even if it didn’t have to. The night out when me and Coco rejoiced over learning that we had used the same word to describe the particular electricity of the exhibition, magic. Not an uncommon word, maybe not one a writer should use proudly. But I was drunk and sentimental that evening and I must protect that feeling, too: the wonder of having carved the same word to describe the same time - a tautology of magic, inspiring, confirming itself. Writing the first draft of this and trying (without success) to define a difference between remembering and reminiscing. I’ve interlaced my heart with yours. Doesn’t matter for how long. Ribbons of yours are woven in with mine. Traces; I hope you feel the same. Thinking a lot about memory, my hometowns. In the first year in Berlin I missed the sea the most and I tried to make the first image of my previous life out of it – gathering lines of poems, pictures real and imagined, the words of friends, too, born by the sea, to make a figure of my own. All along the sea was there, unchanged, with the after-image of me and my brother staring out into it before he left. Me, wondering when meaning would kick into place, fill in the experience. I remember the narrow, internal streets of Pozzuoli – the ample ones of Naples, opening (with a gasp) towards a sudden sky, the sea. What does missing mean? It’s only the heart adjusting. In my first months, I lied to it and let myself reminisce, promising to come back, until it didn’t matter anymore. Corners of Berlin make me cry, now. Every time I walk along Potsdamer Strasse I think of you, of us. The time me and Agata walked three or four bus stations from the Kunstraum and talked about twins and doubles of many kinds and it was sweet to have someone to speak in Italian with. I’ve tried to talk to each of them about the specific shape of this magic. This is what I’ve landed on: the magic was the magic. You should’ve been there. This magic was the magic of us. Of our time: the days of our meeting, the few months we shared, that sacred week before the opening. This magic was the magic of us, doing the thing we love. The magic was us and emanated all around from us and it came and went in waves, because pure feeling is unsustainable, but never went away. I remember blue make-up powder being put in a old salad bowl and then shared. The kitchen, our retreat, which Richie’s costumes made into a backstage, a theatre of its own. Then we went into the exhibition. You must develop a technique. Then you must develop another. You must have a method for summoning and you must not abuse it. You must learn how to distinguish between what must be summoned and what suffices to be recalled or imagined. Don’t call what doesn’t need to called. Dream new dreams. The magic reached its peak in two moments: when I read Tommaso’s words for the second time, after Véra instructed me on how to gather my words. Then, afterwards, when we hosted the second guided tours for strangers who would, in one day, see three or four exhibitions, who knows how many labours of love. We guided them and I felt like, for how much we tried, for how much they wanted to, they’d never be part of the magic, because it belonged to us, it emerged from these months of contact, the daily company in the week of the installation. And I felt we were like children of the same kind, strange and aslant, swimming around in a tight pack, in and out of the swarming schools of strangers, as we hyped up those for whom the time had come to explain their work (with words reasonable and intimate enough), until the moment was over, the light moved to the next piece and we reabsorbed into our group to be congratulated and held. Always a good word, always a work of love. We all hugged in front of Eze's glass trinkets, reflecting complex lights, or maybe not at all. When I called Mattia the last morning of the installation because nothing worked and I was ashamed of being so unprofessional and in the same room with you all he calmed me down and promised me we’d find a way. Mascha helped me put up the pages, stayed with me, patient and with unshakable faith in the success of our endeavour. The last day, before we had to leave, I went and sat down in Lu and Coco’s embryonal space. I closed my eyes, I let the sounds of water and whispers align my breath into a kinder rhythm. I made space for memory, for being there. I knew that something in my heart had shifted (like an old cosmic mechanism commanding the eclipse and the seasons of the moon) as I read the last words of Tommaso. I knew then that, despite my imprecisions, my rushing, my shortcomings, the slips of my pen and my mouth, despite myself, that Tommaso is alive, that he had made it through, that the ritual had been successful. I realized last week, getting sentimental again with Lula, that I’m not done talking about this. I don’t want to exhaust the magic, to say it all. Happiness is honey dripping into the heart. I move around our group like a zealot (in the blue coat Jean-Noël said made me look like a gay wizard), I want to know of everyone, I need everyone of us to know; then I step out of our swarm to see my friends, my boyfriend, to send messages to the absent and the unwilling, because I need to tell everyone that the magic was happiness and I found out that happiness gifts time back.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">storia di tommaso</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/storia-di-tommaso/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="storia di tommaso"/><published>2024-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/storia%20di%20tommaso</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/storia-di-tommaso/"><![CDATA[<p><i>September 2023.</i></p> <p>Exhibition with <a href="https://www.agatahoerttrich.com/queerthingstaketime">Agata Hörttrich</a>, Coco Wiss, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/ezehyon/">Ezequiel Hyon</a>, <a href="https://bueronoelle.com/">Jean-Noël Teschauer</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/jilschuberth/">Jil Schuberth</a>, Lu Herbst, <a href="http://lulabornhak.com/">Lula Bornhak</a>, <a href="https://majazagorska.com/">Maja Zagórska</a>, Mascha Naumann, <a href="https://mattiafriso.com/">Mattia Friso</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/targetlady/">Richard Müller</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/scek_art/">Steve C.E. Knoll</a> and <a href="https://veramariedeubner.com/">Véra Marie Deubner</a>.</p> <p>Storia di Tommaso is a performative story that attempts to tell a queer narrative of becoming, finding identity and purpose outside of the frames of linear storytelling and timelines. Result of the Queer Things Take Time workshop and exhibited in the omonimous exhibition in September 2023, it is a novella informed by concepts of queer temporalities. Set in the first part of the 20th century in South Tyrol, the story is told over multiple languages and perspectives of witnesses to one man’s story who, during the Italian colonisation of the land and its subsequent attack on Ethiopia, tried to define himself across the the frames and temporalities of Christianity and Italianess.</p> <p><em>First cluster: prologue / part V: the gospel of Tommaso / epilogue</em></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster1-1.JPG-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster1-1.JPG-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster1-1.JPG-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster1-1.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Introduction and conclusion to the story with words from the heart of the story, Tommaso's perspective. Installation with writing desk: candle, writing machine, writing paper, portrait and devotional image. Chair, jacket, and string from which the pages hung. At the side of the typewriter, a page invited comments and especially continuations of the story. Some five additions were made by visitors and hung alongside the other pages. </div> <p><em>Second cluster: part I: days of halcyon / part II: body</em></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster2-1.JPG-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster2-1.JPG-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster2-1.JPG-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster2-1.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Tommaso and Johannes' childhood in South Tyrol. Account by Johannes in German, mine in English. Arranged in a tree-like pattern, growing 'sideways'. </div> <p><em>Third cluster - part IV: Bekehrung</em></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster3-1.JPG-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster3-1.JPG-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster3-1.JPG-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster3-1.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Three accounts of Tommaso's conversion in German, English, Italian. Arranged in a spiral-like movement. </div> <p>Collages for the collective <em>Queer Things Take Time zine booklet</em>, one for each session of the workshop: queer apocalypse; queer childhood; queering the archive; queering the public space.</p> <div class="row mt-4"> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine1-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine1-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine2-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine2-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine3-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine3-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine3-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine4-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine4-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine4-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine4.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="storia-di-tommaso;"/><category term="queer-things-take-time"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[September 2023.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">invocation - autofiction *</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/invocation-autofiction-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="invocation - autofiction *"/><published>2024-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/invocation-autofiction-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/invocation-autofiction-1/"><![CDATA[<p><i>May 2023.</i></p> <p>You wake up in the middle of the night – my long-time friend, my other half. You wake in the middle of the night because something has broken the rhythm of your sleep: a distant howl, maybe, a call for some closeness that you too can feel, a sudden thirst. Somebody walks by in the corridor and their approach takes you out of the dream, takes you by surprise when you’re still unable to defend yourself. Now you’re afraid that something is coming and that you cannot stop it and this fear plunges you underwater, where you cannot breathe. But the steps continue beyond your door, and you’re safe again. You could try and sleep some more– you feel the temptation of being lulled back into that sweet nothingness where you don’t have to question your desires and where the memory and fantasies of the boy you once were blend together. But something of the dream’s horniness has stayed with you, and it keeps you awake – a vibration in your body, a distinct arousal; a desire to move the sheets. You wish to come back to that state of youthful bliss, but it’s too late, your mind is slowly finding its way back to you. It now catches up on what your body already knew: that warmth close to you. Something of the dream’s infinite possibilities has stuck with you and you start remembering your dream, green glass shards of a story that first disgusts, then excites you. Memories of the evening that was and the fantasies you have kept inside of you so long, no one to confide them to.</p> <p>over at <a href="https://translucentgreenplasticpress.com/invocation-autofiction-1/"><em>translucent green plastic press</em></a>. Edited by Jonah Lubin and Mona Thierse.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="hermann;"/><category term="invocation;"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[May 2023.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">barndomfragment 2 (lilla huset part I)</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2023/konrad1-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="barndomfragment 2 (lilla huset part I)"/><published>2023-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2023/konrad1-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2023/konrad1-2/"><![CDATA[<style type="text/css">.more_info{border-bottom:1px dotted;position:relative}.more_info .title{position:absolute;top:20px;background:#882d17;color:#3e3f47;text-align:center;padding:6px;left:0}</style> <p><i>Med och till Konrad Karlsson.</i> May-December 2024.</p> <p>🌹 One year before I met you I changed my name, my tongue, my home. Dozing off on the bus from Krumme Lanke to my room in Schlachtensee, I often found myself thinking back to the child I was - this intruder, this unknown, this obstinate dissonance in my story, a him refusing being dealt away with. I found myself stuck between this sudden necessity to remember and the scarceness of my memories, the hardness of those which had coagulated into silence, unspeakability.</p> <p>I looked for a frame for him, something to hold him into place, together. I watched Petite Fille and I found a her and then something else running alongside them, children and phantoms sharing the same game, the same running. The semester we met was quite calm; I was preparing my work. In the following, I read about queer temporalities for the first time, and found out that it had already been written about the child. While José Esteban Muñoz tried to redeem the future (and the value of hope and utopian feeling) from the cynicism of Leo Bersani and Lee Edelmann, the latter argued vehemently against it and, with it, the child, seen as the political vanguard of conservative, homophobic thinking. Writing at the same time as Muñoz, Kathrin Bond Stockton asked: how can we think about the child in a way that is neither utopic nor dismissive? And, what is a child after all?</p> <p>In order to answer that, Stockton makes a critical distinction between the child and the Child; between actual, living (‘historical’) children and the ideological category of the Child, against which real children are confronted and understood. In doing this, she links her argument with Edelman who, in “No Future”, describes the Child as a political plan enacted to secure the ‘future’ exclusively through (heterosexual-ist) reproduction. Consequently, this Child is the ideal continuation of the political ruling class: undoubtedly white, cissexual and straight, imagined as a powerless, a-sexual being in need of constant protection. Any other child - racialised, non-straight, gender-nonconforming, sexual - is not granted this security, is excluded from the category of the Child, from the white matrix, denied empathy, care, protection. As much as Edelmann argues for resistance against the Child and tries to define other worthwhile investments of queer energy, I find Stockton much more interesting, because she centers the life and experience of these real, living children; because she brings me much closer to the child which I actually was.</p> <p>(<span class="more_info" title="Did you feel safe in your childhood?">Kände du dig otrygg i din barndom?</span> Who protected you, and from what? I must’ve been safe because I am white, mostly passed as straight. But it didn’t feel safe. It felt like walking on a line - the balancing effort took all of my energy because I was aware of the dangers that follow transpassing. I think the violence I was exposed to came from that; as if living on a string meant I had deserved it, or that no one would believe me, if I talked. <span class="more_info" title="In which ways were you allowed or not allowed to be a child?">På vilka sätt kände du att du tilläts vara ett barn?</span>)</p> <p>Stockton remarks that, even separating it from the Child, we do not come closer to understanding what a child is. A child is an ineffective definition, understood as it is exclusively in negative terms: as a non-adult, characterized by innocence (as absence of sin, in the sexual sense). Once one escapes the rigid armour of the Child, it becomes clear that this reduction does not and can not account for the complexity of the life of a child: the «pleasures and terrors we recall» <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, shadows of pre-sexuality, the tangled, inexplicable feelings that are too big for words, which almost place one outside of childhood. Somewhere between being a child and remembering the child, in growing up, the transmission goes wrong, and if we settle on the placating definition of ‘child’, <span class="more_info" title="a climate of suspicion, unspeakability, loss, still comes to hover over the real childhoods we had">[MISSING]</span>.</p> <p>It is hard to gauge a child’s understanding of itself, too; self-definition is obstructed by legal and social traditions that decide what a child is, what it should be, by shaping the idea of the Child. This becomes much harder for what we, backwardly, call queer children: when the vocabulary of queerness, of sexual difference, is not made available to the child (too adult, reeking too strongly of sex, of perversion), how can a child express the perceived difference between itself and its surroundings? Despite this, Stockton finds a surprising abundance of metaphors flourishing from children, lapping this very impossibility: one, for example, calling himself a «gay dolphin» (1); weird and aslant expressions that do their best to evade the cage of the category of Childhood. <span class="more_info" title="What did I call myself? What did you call yourself? Was ‘gay’ attractive or painful to you?">Vad sade jag om mig själv? vad sade du om dig själv? var “bög” attraktivt eller kanske sårande för dig?</span>. I stayed in the safety of being unnamed as long as I could. I measure the extent of the violence also by this fact: that I already knew, always knew, that to be named is to be made visible, and to be made visible is to be put in danger. I still ask myself how could I know this. Is there an opposite to growing up - time travel? Did I, as I am and know today, somehow (impossibly) go back and explain to myself the rules of survival, so that I could be safe? Isn’t that the God Augustine calls to - the one which calls back; this conscience which is most easily explained in writing? <span class="more_info" title="Do you see what I mean? Do you see what I mean somewhat more clearly, now?">Förstår du var jag menar? ser du vem du var tydligare än?</span></p> <p>Because of the hardships which she faces in trying to define what a child is, Stockton asks: is there such a thing as a child? <span class="more_info" title="And you - did you ever feel like a child? What did that mean to you?">Och du - kände du dig som ett barn? Vad betydde det för dig?</span>. There is only one possible definition of the child which bears witness to this complexity: «precisely who we are not and, in fact, never were» (5). She concludes, dishearteningly: a child is nothing but <i>«the act of adults looking back»</i> (5, emphasis mine). It is precisely this gesture, this defeat, this holding of complexity, which interests me, because it risks explaining what I felt. Ultimately, Stockton articulates the identity of the child by marking its distinction from the Child, distinguishing between what the child is and what it is wanted to be, what it is accepted to be, but, most importantly, <i>in and through the architecture of memory</i>.</p> <p>Confined in straightjackets of definitions, explained only through negations, every child suffers severe consequences: «such a child, with no established forms to hold itself in the public, legal field, has been a child remarkably, intensely <i>unavailable to itself in the present tense»</i> (6, my emphasis). A child is a being between adulthood and whatever comes before it, caught between its own perception and the invasive gaze of others: a changeling, a bortbyting. Essentially strange, queer, maybe, children exist in a middle space between life and memory, experience and recollection: its life is lived (so Stockton) between one’s own body and the category of the Child. For some of us, for myself, the body itself becomes inaccessible, and it is a life’s work to regain it. What we call a child is the result of a «backward birth» (6), born out of this act of looking back into the being we were and are no more, a retractive creation installed in the process of memory and recollection, between the layers of this one body which becomes double. <span class="more_info" title="Who were you, as a child? Is it still you? Were you always yourself?">[MISSING]</span>.</p> <p>I am trying to articulate, with the help of Stockton’s text, a definition of childhood as a «membrane», an interstitial space, a void in-between, a mezzanine that is barely accessible to the child, but «largely available to adults as memory» (5). The Child imposes itself like a second skin, impossible to distinguish from the first one<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, imposing pressures and limitations, dictating what a child is, what it cannot be. A troubling degree of voyeurism haunts this definition: the child spies through the keyhole of the Child (of its body its memory) into others, into the other children and the space of living they are afforded, into the mysterious life of the adults, and into itself, its own life, body, experiences.</p> <p>As I move across my memories, to try and revive them, to make sense of what happened, as I try and access this membrane, the «the pleasures and terrors» woven in its fabric - the memories, real or not, of the Mumin beheading, of that vast blue silence, all of the things I can’t say yet - <span class="more_info" title="I am not returning to the child, but inventing it">[MISSING]</span>. I describe him with a vocabulary of feeling and identity that is available to me only, only in the afterwards, having reached ‘adulthood’. And the child changed too, over the years - depending on the time of access, as my understanding of myself changed, as it became necessary to either install or rescue strands of emotions and thoughts that I see continuing now, in the aftermath. Said with Stockton, the child is ultimately an effect of memory, as intangible as it is, an ever-imperfect attempt to resolve the first queer autobiographical question: «when did you know?» (2). This matter can be hardly settled and approached only retroactively, by turning one’s gaze towards the past which couldn’t be defined in the time of its presence. Only as an adult can I look back - and this child must die, give way to me, for me to be able to call him queer. His death must be accompanied by another death: the death of what Stockton calls the “straight child”, a manifestation of the Child structure highlighting the pressures and expectations that are supposed to catapult the child from its presumed a-sexuality into open heterosexuality. I must declare the death of the straight child for me to find the queer child - this unknown who lived desperately and proficiently in lack and in need of words, in hiding. It is only at a basic removal, at some distance - an international move, so many years of forgetting - that I might be able to reconcile myself with that child, to give it the space it needed. <span class="more_info" title="How far I’ve had to go to find you">[MISSING].</span></p> <p>There is, of course, a significant degree of arbitrarity to this. How can I say with any certainty: <span class="more_info" title="_I was a queer child?_ Were you? Can anyone be?"><i>jag var queen som barn?</i> Var du? Kan man ens vara det?</span> Every language proves insufficient, every vocabulary fails. I always had, like any child, complex desires for touch, proximity, affection, and they extended both to little girls and little boys. I don’t know if that’s enough to invoke queerness. I cannot know of my gender, too, if my sense of being non-binary today (this refusal of loud, brawling masculinity, this move towards gender expansion, questioning) can be traced back to my little games and aversions; which is to say, if I can extend my understanding of myself this far into the past. I have found hints, not one proof. I can’t say anything for certain - whether I was or wasn’t a boy, if I wanted to be; if boyhood ever meant anything to me or if it was just the hide that’d keep me the safest. <span class="more_info" title="My memories shift and spill like watercolour, and I don’t know where to begin">[MISSING]</span>. Stockton’s discourse, in her intentional, sweeping generalization of childhood as queer, pays the just tribute to the complexities of childhood; to the very real experience of conflicting feelings, statements, oblique and cross desires that (this somehow I remember so clearly) occur daily in a child’s mind, before we must learn to give it confines, before the walls are made to rise, so much taller than us.</p> <p>In this light, recollection appears as the process not just to bring memories back to oneself, but to re-inhabit the space between who one is and was, between the remembering adult and the remembered child, as well as the membrane between the child and the Child, the space of experience of the child itself, in which the feelings appeared and the memories were produced. I must declare this process impossible, too. Recollection always fails: the memories are volatile, ever-changing, prone to defect, corruption. The child remains unexplainable, inaccessible.</p> <p>I believe in this. But I know there’s degrees to the unfathomability of childhood. Maybe there are some truths about yours: memories you feel you can trust. But that’s not true for me. I have forgotten so much that was essential to who I was and the few memories which remain are the ones I cannot look at yet. All of this rests on a simple fact: I’m not sure what happened. (I was made not to be sure about what happened). I had to forget, to distance myself from the event, the memory.</p> <p>This matters not because I want to prove an essentialist sense of queerness, a timeline which from childhood leads directly into my present now - but because queerness, I believe, is a way of kinship, of connection - if I were a queer child, what (or who) can I connect that child with? What theories might I use to understand him? The result is this impossible answer - or rather, a multiplication of answers, all imperfect, all temporary, which give way into writing, into these words I try to give you.</p> <p>Sharpening a definition of “child” that accounts for these <i>pleasures and terrors</i> also makes space for this desire we have, as the last generation that grew between the offline and the online, when the Internet was a world still mysterious, both infinite and very small - between proto-Youtube and school courtyard tales, to find the scary and the traumatising in the medias of our childhood. I cannot claim to have taken part in any of the Mandela effects that could’ve been accessible to me as an Italian kid growing up in the early 2000s, but I remember reading scary stories on Italian blogs (bad translations, but still effective), being terrorized by forcing myself to watch TV documentaries on the seven apparitions of Mary, the Mothman or reptilians; accessing the chunky Youtube of the time to watch videos about Lavender Town, being scared sleepless about its implications: dying of frequencies that only a child could hear. Years later, I would find the Troll i kulisserna/Mumintrollet story, and invest in it so deeply that I couldn’t help but write about it - the moment from which all of this started.</p> <p>(<span class="more_info" title="What does this say about me, about my childhood? Where do I go from here?">Vad säger det om mig, om barndom? Det barn jag tydligen varit?</span>)</p> <p><span class="more_info" title="Terror was the easiest way I could reach myself">[MISSING]</span>; nothing brought me back to my body as efficiently as night sweats, extending my eyes into the room at night to see what I wanted to see, what I feared I would see, if only I tried hard enough, which I had to in order to protect myself; playing with turning the TV on and off, closing and opening the creepypasta blogs - fort, da. Mask on, off.</p> <p>Stockton touches only lightly on trauma in reference to Freud’s theory of Nachträglichkeit, his original understanding of trauma as “deferred action”, an impression that is impossible for the (child) brain to process and incorporate and, as such, remains latent in the mind. This unprocessed knot of feelings and memory can be later activated during a re-exposure, when a similar event brings out the original traumatic memory, or during psychoanalysis. Only through this activation is the original traumatic event constructed, <i>retroactively</i> (nachträglich), as such, and that its latent effect (protecting the psyche by avoiding situations that could’ve re-ignited it) becomes seen and understandable. Like the child, trauma is created posthumously. But Stockton remarks a fundamental difference: the child can be aware of this state of deferral, of its delay; it might « await only (the right to claim) a word, not a mental state of being, withheld from them in childhood.» (15).</p> <p><span class="more_info" title="As a child I was so terribly aware of myself.">Som barn var ja så förfärligt självmedveten.</span> I tried to grow up as quickly as I could, I shifted into a space within myself where, in hiding, I would observe the adults, their mannerisms, the topics of their conversations, and tried my best to emulate them. The result of my efforts was a grotesque parody, something sombre, saddening and slightly troubling - more <i>bortbytling</i> than child. I really started to think of myself as an adult in a child’s body, because there was no space for me to hold my feelings and remain a Child. I became reckless, desperate, to grow up: I walked away with disgust from any diminutives, any -ino (which meant walking away from myself, too, as a bambino), from anything I perceived childish, from age-appropriate books; I insisted on inflating my vocabulary with big and abstruse words, and delighted when the adults, halfway buying my performance, talked to me as an adult, sometimes confided in me. Now I can’t help but see the dangers of being perceived as older. <span class="more_info" title="I don’t know if this was a consequence of the abuse or a prelude to it.">Jag vet inte om det var en konsekvens av misshandel.</span> Eventually, when the first hairs started poking out of my upper lip, I celebrated a sad victory - somehow knowing already that, though an era of powerlessness was coming to its end, becoming a boy would bring its unique and terrifying consequences, too. (How could I have known already?)</p> <p>When I look back to my memories, my point of view hangs far above my eyes, somewhere over my head. It’s always been like this and I cannot tell, now, whether this was a practical consequence of my emotional and physical dissociation, or the aftereffect of my distance as an adult which I install in the past. As if there had been some truth to my feeling of being an adult in a child’s body, I see myself as if I were walking by my side, a vaporous conscience above myself. As an image, it indicates quite nicely that it is impossible to define who I was without acknowledging where I’m throwing my gaze from now, as well as that there wouldn’t be a child without the adult to remember him. There would not be an adult without a child who, despite everything, including himself, made it through.</p> <p>Being a child, living inside of this membrane, <span class="more_info" title="at the same time inside and outside childhood">[MISSING]</span>, must’ve meant living halfway there, halfway here. Never fully in one place, never able to produce a clear, uncontestable memory. This membrane, the space I retreated inside of as a child and at the same time the difference between who I am now and who I was, becomes the access point to my life - present or past. If it still makes sense to distinguish between the two. <span class="more_info" title="I lost the child, I lost memory.">Jag förlorade barnet och jag förlorade minnet.</span></p> <p>Inside the room of childhood, I listen to the sounds from the neighboring walls, observe the flickering of a flame through their semi-transparent fabric. Someone’s in the other room. These walls are the membrane - some of them hardened by the Child, obstructing communication, sight. My life is happening in the other room. I can see shadows of it, never the whole. He can see me too - how far I’ve come - but not enough. I hope it’s enough to vaporize into hope for him, what we used to call destiny, or the god of broken cobblestones. The wall is a womb and a thick membrane and, through the blood, the amniotic liquid, the light sometimes shines through, and sometimes I can see him looking back at me. Most of the time the bortbytling keeps quiet, and I know he’s there just because of the way the light hits his figure, casting a terrible shadow. Some nights I find it’s myself, not him, to be wailing. In the hours before dawn, as the candleflame dies and the sun is gone, it sometimes becomes impossible to distinguish between him, who managed to survive childhood, and me who’s been survived. There’s always a wailing, always a calling - <span class="more_info" title="to make sure that, on the other side, there’s someone listening.">ett kall som säkerställer att, på andra sidan, ha någon som lyssnar.</span></p> <p>For both of us, desire for «meaningful plenitude»<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> is impossible. We wish to see what’s in the other room, what has or will happen, but we can’t. We make the best of ourselves out of the glimpses we catch, incorporating them into bigger narratives which, with time, we must shed like snakeskin. Complete vision - complete memory - is impossible. I sit in the room and listen, my ear to the wall.</p> <p>Maybe I am allowed a childhood only now that I am out of the labyrinth. The memories of what hurt are crystallised, safeguarded, and the membrane between me and them is surprisingly clear, though opaque. Awaiting, maybe, «the right to claim a word» I don’t know yet, or knew all along. As I look to the wall in front of me, I create the child in the other room, and the difference between imagination and memory gets thinner. He rebels, of course, and I must pay attention to do right by him. In this membrane, past and present merge into one, and I am left with this calling, the grief of this unbridgeable distance, and the vague shape of a future project on a wall I haven’t turned to in so long.</p> <p>🌹 We talk about this. I convince you. We spend a long afternoon, then a long evening, trying to translate all of this into your mother tongue, rushed by a deadline I wasn’t careful enough to anticipate. I sit on the sofa, you at the desk, working away. Sometimes you ask me what I mean with this or that. I try to tell you, but the afternoon’s fight still reverberates across my ability to explain myself. I don’t want to do this anymore.</p> <p>Every other time that we talked about this - me writing about my childhood, about us - you sounded excited. I was happy to see you involved, interested in my work. But this is not what I wanted. You resent me for this.</p> <p>It will take me a long time - even after Gotland - to realize that I had messed up my expectations, the workload. All of this because I couldn’t say this: will you please look at this I wrote? It’s for you. It’s about you. I want you to be part of it, too. I want our names to exist together, next to one another, on a page.</p> <p>🌹 We fought once and, in the crying and reconciling that comes afterwards, you were pointedly honest and said something that I didn’t think would’ve hurt me. Then, to my surprise, I found a breathlessness rising in my chest and I observed myself as I ran to the bathroom, locked myself in there. In the memory, the camera follows me from above, like some kind of action scene, or a nature documentary. <span class="more_info" title="You ran after me and waited outside, terrified.">Du sprang efter mig och väntade utanför, förskräckt.</span> Inside, I dealt with the first panic attack of my life. In the mist-like texture of memory, which is also my life, the words you had said on the sofa mixed themselves curiously with my mother’s voice, even though I can’t ever remember her saying anything similar to what you did, my body reacted to it nonetheless. When I got out, you apologized. I was delighted. The panic your words caused in me proved two things: first, that our relationship had alchemized that unique chemistry of safety and challenge, allowing us to keep moving; secondly, the existence of something true inside of myself, a feeling of hurt so deep and unquestionable that it had to mobilize my whole body to work through it. It proved that I had actually been hurt - that the memories were not wrong; <span class="more_info" title="that they could be awakened - by you.">att dom kunde väckas till liv - av dig.</span></p> <p>🌹 I had never really looked at that picture. This is the only picture of my childhoodI still have on my computer. I was playing a little violet plastic piano, he a silver saxophone, also plastic. I don’t know if I’m smiling, smirking, or looking a little terrified at the camera. It changes everytime I look.</p> <p>We are standing in front of our desk. We are right in front of the one that, years later, would become mine. We never changed them. I just remembered I used to hide in there. I would put my face against the little space between the desk and the wall, where a little cold air would come through, and breathe really slowly. So as to no make a sound.</p> <p>I cry for a few seconds, then it’s over again.</p> <p>🌹 It gets better. We forget the incident. The excitement of being done with it also helps. I receive your impressions of the project, I archive them inside of them. I share a few of mine, trying not to hurt either of us. But we did it. We didn’t give up on this. We land on something different than what I had imagined - something which, over time, I will begin to recognise as ours.</p> <p>🌹 As I was researching this text, I began reading more about Tove Jansson. I found out that, as per the custom of the time, she referred to lesbians (and herself) as “ghosts”.</p> <p>🌹 We didn’t watch All of Us Strangers (Haigh, 2023) together. I needed a space of feelings encumbered by anyone else’s presence, by their feelings, their reaction to mine. (I went with Eesha, but we agreed to sit at opposite sides of the movie hall and reconvene later.) It’s also true that I’m not very good at letting you in. When we talked about it, later, I tried to tell you about what I had seen, but I failed. <span class="more_info" title="But this is me trying.">Men det här är jag som försöker.</span></p> <p>One of the most striking moments happens when, halfway across the movie, Adam stays the night in the impossible house of his parents. As he wakes up from troubled sleep, he’s wearing the pajama of his childhood self, strained painfully, comically, over his adult body, like a costume. As with Stockton’s membrane, Adam accesses his childhood by re-inhabiting the skin (clothes) of the child he was, making memory physical, a space that can be embodied, allowing him access to the his childhood in an unprecedented way. These are the last moments of Adam’s journey into the past, as the membrane becomes the thinnest, the most dangerous. When he, unable to sleep, slips into his parent’s bedroom and has a nighttime conversation with his mother, he finds out that, in this trespassing of the barrier between adult and child, all of his terror and grief which inhabited his childhood have made it through, too. Like a child, he’s looking for reassurance: Like Stockton’s child and Freud’s Nachträglichkeit, the past must be reactivated in order to be made available, to be processed. In the beginning of the movie, Adam lives a monotonous and safe life, until a chance encounter with someone he’d like to love acts as a catalyst for the mechanism of memory. Only after Harry, because of him, does the membrane between childhood and adult self become available and Adam gets to meet his parents, who died in a car accident when he was little. Only after knowing them as an adult, and letting himself be known (coming out, too), does the continuation of the story, and love, become possible.</p> <p>After the night in his parent’s house Adam wakes up in his own bed and finds shelter from his night terror in Harry. As he stands up, Adam opens up for the first time and tells him of the grief of losing his parents, the uncomfortableness of growing up in the aftermath of HIV, moving to the big city, losing friends, finding himself stuck in a life without much joy but also without pain. All of this, he admits, mixed to become the same feeling: « I felt like the future didn’t matter ».</p> <p><span class="more_info" title="Our disagreement over the movie lay in the fact that you read it as a ghost story and a tragedy and I couldn’t">Vår oenighet över filmen ligger i faktumet om att du ser den som en tragedi.</span></p> <p>Adam has one last lunch with his parents and, this time, gets to say goodbye to them. Afterwards, instead of going to his apartment and waiting for Harry to come up, he heads to his place for the first time. As he opens the doror, he finds his friend’s body, rotting. Harry enters the room and Adam tries to convince him to go out, but he insists on staying, admitting, in between tears, that he can smell his own body. He must’ve killed himself months before, when, after their first meeting, Adam (still crystallized in his loneliness and grief) rejected him. But he eventually manages to convince him and, in the last scene, Adam hugs Harry in his own bed, as the camera pans away from them, until nothing but darkness and one bright star appear. You saw that as the last moment of happiness granted to them. But I don’t think so. When Adam carries Harry into his room, he’s not just accompanying him towards the light. In the scene before, as they find Harry’s body, it can be identified because it is wearing the same clothes he was wearing during that first encounter - the same salmon sweater that Harry wears when he enters the room, carrying the same bottle of gin that he offered Adam at his doorstep, before he rejected him. In Harry’s room, the past of his death coexists with a present in which he is still alive.</p> <p>I believe that, as Adam went back to touch the membrane of his childhood, he became able to break the one that separates the past from the present, too. As he intervenes to stop Harry from touching his own body, as he hugs him to sleep, <span class="more_info" title="he’s not accepting his death: he’s re-writing history, he’s changing the past.">en gåva, ledandes in i en ny framtid, som gjordes möjlig genom att ändra det förflutna.</span> His engagement with the past has awakened the dead, yes, but also made other configurations of the present possible; coming from an alternative future in which he did have a relationship with Harry, he visits the past of that first night and is able to intervene in it, to save Harry, to establish a new time.</p> <p>This is what I wanted to tell you. I don’t want us to be ghosts. I want happiness for us now.</p> <p>I’m trying to learn how to read hope, baby.</p> <p>🌹 What else I can say about my childhood:</p> <p>As a child I was not safe. None of us were. I was aware of this and aware that it was wrong to feel like this. Because my heartbreak and my grief and my anger could not be held anywhere, because I was required to live in unsafe conditions without the power to change them, I created an ever-growing distance between myself, my body and feelings. To feel in charge, to regain some sense of control, I played with the balance between safety and danger, with horror, scaring myself and others. So much of what happened, of what I was set to become, was outside of my control. The mask was taken off even when I asked it to stop. I had to watch it happen all throughout my childhood. One moment you’re safe, the next you’re not. This child is alive in me and he sometimes screams at you for what you ask of me, for what you don’t give, for what I don’t know how to ask.</p> <p>But I also know something else. <span class="more_info" title="I’m trying to tell you that there was a kernel of you in my childhood.">Jag försöker berätta för dig att det fanns en kärna av dig i min barndom.</span> I’ve been trying to gather the pieces, to write it all together, and I wanted you to have a part, too. Because if my memory remains shadowy, exposed to stronger winds that bend it and shape it beyond my will, if the whole category of childhood couldn’t sustain me, couldn’t keep me safe, then maybe I was never a child, if anyone can be. Maybe I’m just learning now how to be one. Maybe you’re teaching me.</p> <p>If whatever child I can call to is a construction, if I cannot penetrate the membrane anyhow, if I am doomed to living with the ghost of him, then maybe I can see that he’s still here, and I did save him, I did save us; andif my memory is intangible and changeable, if both queerness and the absence of it are inventions, if I cannot write what happened without being so fucking afraid that someone would dismiss it, challenge it, counter it – if there are no facts now that I can appeal to, if there wasn’t anyone ever to help me, then I was never inside of the reality of the Child. Maybe, then, I can take that skin off and write a different story, call it autobiography. In it, zapping through afterhours Italian TV channels, I did stumble upon a Mumin cartoon – upon Tofslan och Vifslan, lovers or twins, and the Groke, who didn’t frighten me. Maybe my father did go to Sweden, and he brought something sweet and intangible, a handful of perfect snow, which I picked up from the nightstand before I left. If I have no recollections I can serve myself with, then I can take the leap and call my writing my memory.</p> <p>If there was a time in which the two of us were kids at the same time, I can record this simple chronological fact in sequence and make it aslant by adding <i>tilsammans</i>. The story, impossible to prove, goes: on one afternoon of primary school the child you were, your left hand still unscarred, took the hand of the child I was in the courtyard, and the affection we discovered in that September of two years ago has not been invented, it rather moved across history from that one afternoon towards this time and space, to meet the people we are, who have forgotten, and illuminate childhood with its possibility.</p> <p>Because if you were there, in my childhood – then it becomes easier for me to believe that there was goodness there, too, and kindness and understanding and love, and that the punishment for my trespasses didn’t ruin me; I then remember that I wasn’t alone, I never was, and that there was play too, and fun, because despite my malaise, my terminal seriousness, we play sometimes and it’s nice, it’s just fucking nice, and sometimes we play this game called ‘fantasy of a house’ where I tell you why I sometimes lash out at you and you tell me why you can’t believe my good faith – the missing page, that which will not be written.</p> <p>Eventually we go to bed. Turning the light off, you ask me to hug you and I do, just before you fall asleep, you before me always. With my head full of the work of the day (the dissatisfaction with the way words flow, the rare moments where it becomes easy), I see clearly that, in this little bed, we are moving back in time as well as onwards, while being perfectly grounded in the present, like a sturdy island in a storm; then, for the first time in my life, the future opens up like the sea, infinite and safe, seen from <span class="more_info" title="this happy room we write together.">i detta lyckliga rum vi skrev tilsammans.</span></p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1"> <p>Kathryn Bond Stockton, The Queer Child, or Growing Sideways in the Twentieth Century, Duke University Press, 2009, page 6. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2"> <p>TThis connection between temporal regimes (as the Child, ultimately, is a way to control that phase of human growth) and somatic experience brings me back to an insight of Elizabeth Freeman, who, in “Time Binds”, described the chrononormative nature of capitalistic, heterosexualist time as a «somatic fact», that is to say, the way that thisis made to appear natural because of its inscription into the body and its rhythms/cycles. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3"> <p>The quote is from Samyel Delaney’s “The Motion of Light in Water”, Arbor House, 1998, quoted in José Esteban Muñoz, Cruising Utopia: The Then and There of Queer Futurity, NYU Press, 2019, page 59. I interpolate this image of the room from Delaney’s autobiographical account of seeing Allan Kaprow’s “Eighteen Happenings in Six-Parts”. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>