<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-12-07T10:21:08+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">barndom fragments 1 (lilla huset part I)</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/konrad1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="barndom fragments 1 (lilla huset part I)"/><published>2024-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/konrad1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/konrad1/"><![CDATA[<style type="text/css">.more_info{border-bottom:1px dotted;position:relative}.more_info .title{position:absolute;top:20px;background:#e0dacf;color:#3e3f47;text-align:center;padding:4px;left:0}</style> <p><i>With and for Konrad Karlsson.</i> May-December 2024.</p> <p><br/> <img src="https://marialaurids.net/assets/blog_posts/posts/Screenshot 2024-05-27 113548.png" alt="A zoomed-in screenshot of a picture on a computer, showing a child with a confused look on his face, playing on a." width="100%" height="100%"/></p> <p><i>25 ‎May ‎2024, ‏‎12:37:</i></p> <p><i><span class="more_info" title="You never told me about Troll in the Wings.">Du berätta aldrig om troll i kulisserna för mig. </span> I found out about it last year, in one of those August afternoons I spent lazily browsing on my computer while you worked in the other room. The play, the second official Mumin theatre adaptation written by Tove Jansson and directed by Vivica Bandler, is known today mostly because of its beginning, in which the Mumin actors enter the stage with usual, intact costumes to then remove their fluffy heads – unmasking, amongst others, the perfectly childish smirk of Lasse Pöysti, playing Moomintrollet. This was ostensibly done to give the actors more freedom with voice and facial expressions, but a dark-internet myth has gathered around the play: children in the audience terrorized by this quasi Mumin decapitation, revealing horribly out-of-place humans inside their white, rotund bodies. With the following performances and the TV broadcast the incident was repeated, making the play into a uniting traumatic memory for generations of Swedish children.</i></p> <p> When I started writing this in May, I wanted to talk about childhood – mine and yours, or rather, the projection of mine on yours, because you don’t like talking about the past and I try to respect that. In the following months, with the following rewrites, I set out to find more information on this play. I was hoping to see the taking-off of the masks – to hear, if not see, the children’s reaction – but I haven’t been able to find any clips of it. In the (unofficial) Mumin wiki, which my research history states I consulted, this ‘decapitation’ is mentioned without any horrific undernotes. Were children really scared? Where did I get the idea that they were? I can't find any other hint in my web search chronology or online. While the absence of proof solidifies the status of the event as a myth, there must’ve been another source, expanding on the story to prove, once more, the Internet’s strange passion for finding the grotesque, the uncanny, the not-quite-right, the traumatising in children’s stories. And that I hadn’t just invented it. </p> <p> You have, of course, no memory of Troll I kulisserna. You were born too late; the Mumin stories you grew up with were different, safe, an uncomplicated background: there, but never essential. <span class="more_info" title="But were there other stories of horror that captured you, when you were young?">Med fanns det någon annan marginell skräck från sagor som fängslade dig när du var liten?</span> You became uneasy when, during one of my marathons, I showed you the ’70 Mumin episode in which Mårran appears for the first time. After asking me to press stop, you told me of how deeply unsettling it was, as a child, to see her towering over Sniff; mysterious, cold, silent. A creature one couldn’t make sense of, couldn’t speak to. Did you have to distinguish, then, between what your eyes just saw and the child’s memory, enlarged, made stranger against the backdrop of your mind?</p> <p> Whether I came up with it or someone else, the question is: what feelings, fake or real, were activated and subsumed into the memory of the Mumin beheading as it was passed on, shared, confused, installed in the precarious architecture of recollection - which <span class="more_info" title="pleasures and terrors">«njutningar och fasor»</span>, otherwise unspeakable, found their expression in it?</p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 I was gifted the complete edition <span class="more_info" title="in translation">(iöversatt)</span> of the original Tove Jansson Mumin strips for my eighteenth birthday, long before I met you. I was only a little into them, mostly fascinated by Snufkin, but it was the gift of a friend trying to share her passion for them with me. When I told you, did you feel that I was being ungenuine, maybe inventing, doing too much - or that I was trying to steal from the cultural depository of your childhood? Is this how you felt about the latest 3D animated series, made for an international audience with puzzling British accents, that also moved me?</p> <p>Or did you just not care - had it been that long?</p> <p><span class="more_info" title="But you gifted me a Snufkin cup for my birthday last year.">Ändå gav du mig en Snusmumriken-kopp i födelsedagspresent förra året.</span> Were you letting me in on the secret, your childhood, the one thing we cannot share, no matter how much I’d like to - were you welcoming me into it or just indulging me and my childish desires?</p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 <span class="more_info" title="I don’t remember my childhood and that’s one of the few things I can say with certainty about it.">Jag minns inte mycket från min barndom, och det är en av få saker for mjag kan säga med säkerhet.</span> Another one: you weren’t there. But then again, I wasn’t either. And not just in the sense that I, the person I’ve come to be, do not and cannot live there anymore - the basic fact that the membrane of childhood doesn’t allow trespassing: «my infancy is long dead and I am alive»[^1]; but because I barely lived in that house, consumed by the business of survival, which makes ghosts of us all. My memory, the second house, made into a broken sieve, unfit for my purposes, the tasks of life.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 I look through my notes, I look back. But I find nothing - neither proof that someone else did write about Troll i kulisserna's traumatic past, nor that I, for some reason, invented it. Reading this again, I think: if the Internet had been as it was ten, fifteen years ago - could I have started something? Do you think that someone would’ve believed me? Troll i kulisserna could’ve been one of those stories in which Internet subculture, with its inclination towards morbidity, interacts with the loose fabric of memory, which is all the looser in childhood, remaining malleable, mobile, decades after its imprinting.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 Writing about myself is easy, as long as nobody sees. Writing about us is hard. I’m looking for a frame for us, a crowd for this room. Generations of queers have gathered in private places [^2], celebrating newborn tongues and attending to the wounds of the first years, when everything passes through the skin, that unfit membrane. When we met I went in headfirst because I felt that you could take it, that you wanted to - <span class="more_info" title="and I hope you felt the same">och jag hoppas att du kände likadant.</span> I felt myself falling in love with you (clearly, secretly) when, p you sat on my bed and told me of the child you were, of the story behind the scar on your left hand. I wanted to pick it up and kiss it; I don’t remember if I did. We had known each other for less than two weeks. Somewhere on your phone you have a screen recording archiving our first chats and witnessing a miraculous fact: that, in that often crude place where we met, the first pictures we sent each other were of the seas of our hometowns. There, amidst the yellow and the black, I saw the shores of Gotland and thought: I’d like to go there. Then: I think he gets it; «… <span class="more_info" title="the one pain / which is inconsolable">den smärta / som är så</span>, the loss of one’s shore …» [^3]</p> <p><span class="more_info" title="Was it easy to receive the story of my childhood?">Var det enkelt att höra om min barndom?</span> In the beginning I wanted to tell you of the places I had escaped so that I could come to this city, where I would meet you. I wanted to put everything in sequence and see what meaning would come from it. What role you could play. Now this retroactive act is necessary to both of us, because it explains me, my resistances to you. In truth - only in telling does the pain become evident, and I can begin. Unlike Augustine, I have no God to call to, no omniscient eternal perspective to allow the retrieval of childhood under the image of eternity, the beginning act of the Western autobiography. I do not know where to begin. I need another context, an excuse - a song, a movie, a book. <span class="more_info" title="You, listening.">Du, som lyssnar.</span></p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 I’m reading about queer memory. It’s shaping up to be a weird semester: pausing uni, trying to get therapy, writing about something new, somewhat more, somehow always less. After a few months of not approaching theory, I started reading Castiglia and Reed’s sad and exciting essay, <i>If Memory Serves</i>, on the effects of remembering and (institutional, collective) forgetting in the aftermath of AIDS. I think I need to go to the roots - of queer temporalities, of queer theories, of us, somehow, because we all exist in a world irrevocably shaped by it. <span class="more_info" title="I’m trying to learn. I’m trying to remember.">Jag försöker lära mig. Jag försöker förstå.</span></p> <p>I’ve always known that my personal memory was tattered and broken; I am starting to see that I never accessed a social, generational one as well. I have been severed not just from myself, but from an entire history of queerness - of Italian queer and trans activists (Porpora Marcasciano, Mario Mieli) who created the space in which I could’ve found rest and solace, had I dared to. But I couldn’t. The business of survival cut what remained of the thread of memory, it required me to disconnect from myself and the stories before and around me. When I walked to my high school or across the tiny streets that suddenly give way into big squares and churches in Naples, when my father drove me back home late at night, I looked away from the trans women strutting by. Was that survival again? Wasn’t that immediate fear which struck at the sight of them the beginning of this betrayal to myself, my history? This happened much later, when I wasn’t a child anymore. But I always knew where to look and, most importantly, where not to. And how can I draw a clear line between the child and the teen, when that child never died and was never really there and I live in the long aftermath of him, too?</p> <p>(I can’t say what was that severed. I can’t say yet.)</p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 Maybe I did invent this story about Troll i kulisserna.</p> <p>In trying to make sense of this, I realize that what I find so fascinating about this mishap is its shift in logic. Although the removal of the Mumin masks has a practical explanation, that moment can be read also as revealing a raw materiality in the otherwise intact body of the Mumin. The consequences, which are immediately understood by children, are: their soft skin can be taken off; their fluffy bodies can be emptied out and inhabited by something different; this, of course, if it wasn’t a costume, a decoy, all along. This revelation raises a morbid question: what is a Mumin, actually? Is it an animal that can be killed and whose hide can be worn - or a strategy of prey? Who hides, then, in their big, friendly bodies? Why is Lasse Pöysti’s smile so unsettling? <span class="more_info" title="Danger in Moominvalley">Fora i Mumindalen - the safest of places</span>. Through this logic, the familiar and inconspicuous bodies of Muminpappa and Muminmamma become <span class="more_info" title="a skin - a membrane">en hud - ett membran</span>, as changeable as memory itself, the unstable resource for this story: mine, unable to find my sources anymore, and that of those children who, writing about it online, would’ve re-membered the event years after its passing, bringing that fear back to themselves; not unlike you, unable to stand the sight of Mårran.</p> <p>🌹 In that same August, you picked out a dub of the original 1969 Mumin anime with the original finlandssvenska accent for me, the one you grew up next to. My childhood didn’t have an accent. We watched Italian dubs of anime with the pedantic, impersonal Italian that doesn’t really belong anywhere. It was the first hint that there is not such a thing as Italy, but I wouldn’t get it until, in Berlin, I noticed that my longing called for the seas of my hometowns, Napoli och Pozzuoli, not for whatever sea touches the nation. I was ashamed of liking these shows publicly because of the kinship they inspired - Dragonball with the rowdy boy friends of my childhood, Marmalade Boy with the girls I had fragile and tentative friendships with. (I’m older now and I’m trying not to be ashamed of what I like. I bought myself a green fleece pälsmössa-like hat with a Snufkin design for my birthday; when things got dark in August, I watched the Mumin you had shown me - three, four episodes in a row, at times.) </p> <p>Talking about Astrid Lindgren and Tove Jansson at our first dinner, your mother got teary-eyed. My father would get emotional about the Carlo Collodi stories he read as a boy. When I approached those heavy hardbacks, with their distinctly old design with a suspicious interest in order, I found them too Christian, too moralising, the language too old, too distant. My childhood, the real one, the one that came and went, wasn’t sustained by any Italian narration of childhood. The entrusting of stories from one generation to the next didn’t happen for me in the same way it did for you and maybe that’s why I latched on to yours so strongly - so strangely, so backwardly, years before I met you. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹Sometimes, out of nowhere, I get worried that your birthday passed and I didn’t get you anything. But I wrote you a letter. I always forget I did. I won’t repeat what it said, but I did tell you that writing a letter to you was a way to let you into this place, the only home I have; to solidify your place in the architecture of my mind, to make you part of the energy that sustains me. I sometimes think, out of the blue: there’s a queer future ahead of us. Whatever that means, it begins with a paragraph which features us both, under the rubric of an unlikely ‘us’. I know it exists because I will it - I write it. </p> <p>But for this to work, I have to trust you. <span class="more_info" title=" I have to entrust myself - my voice - to you.">Jag måste lita på mig själv - min röst – till dig.</span></p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹<span class="more_info" title=" Growing up, my father used to tell me of the time that, when he was young and on his pilgrimage to the North Pole, he stopped in Sweden. ">Under min uppväxt brukade min pappa berätta om den gången han var ung och stannade till i Sverige under sin pilgrimsfärd till Nordpolen.</span> He told me people got naked as often as possible, were very sexually open and every meal was served with jam and milk. This, as well as a few other hints like IKEA names and midsummar poles, was the context I evoked to make sense of you. But when I told you, you just laughed and said my father must’ve been somewhere else. It hurt me a bit to hear. I still repeated this anecdote over the second dinner with your parents, to be conversational and pleasant. I thought of my parents then - what language they would use to talk with you. The bravado that my father would summon to put together the very few English words he knows with whatever linguistic souvenirs of this mythological trip he could resurrect, in the spirit of that specifically Neapolitan brand of arrogance, the unfounded belief that, with their hand dialect and scraps of English, they can make themselves understood across any linguistic divide. I have no idea what my mother would do. She would probably ask me to translate, or count on her grimaces, kept alive by working with children, to communicate with you. But I won’t allow for the three of you to sit at that kitchen table; the pictures that my father took of this alleged Sweden rest somewhere in his nightstand, and I remember taking another look at them before I left - proof that, even shortly, one of us could leave. Two years ago, I asked him to send some of them to me. <span class="more_info" title=" That was the necessary prologue to me telling them about you. ">Det var den nödvändiga uppbyggnad som behövdes för att jag skulle berätta om dig för dem. </span> But he forgot, I didn’t press him, and then I stopped answering the phone when he called. Trying my hardest to make something different of my tongue, to twist it in different sounds. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹A memory is a chance and a liability. Allowing it invites pain in and pain always brings you back to yourself, the small confines of your body, and for the longest time I couldn’t be in that room, because it was the least safe. I’m learning how to be there - how to just be. To overcome the haunting, make the space habitable. <span class="more_info" title=" To have a spare bed, when you come over. ">Att ha en extrasäng till dig när du sover över. </span> </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 Then finally I figure it out. </p> <p>Looking at the Mumin wiki again for answers, I find this passage, ignored until now: <i>The same practice would return to great controversy in the 1969 show.</i> I follow the hint and it all begins to make sense. In the 1969 TV broadcast series “Mumintrollet”, a king gets hay fever by looking at the Mumin through a telescope, and orders for their snouts to be removed. While in the first episode they move (quite goofily) across the Muminhuset in their usual costumes, in the second episode a secondary character keeps Mumintrollet tied down after having tied his head to the door knob, so that when Muminpappa enter the room, the camera shows his head flying towards him. Again Lasse Pöysti’s face appears underneath, visibly shocked, touching his eyes and face, lamenting the loss of his näsa. </p> <p>This is, somehow, much worse than what I had thought - the closest we can get to a real decapitation in a Mumin story. As I had to make peace with the idea that I came up with the story, I am shocked at how closely what I wrote about it resembles the actual show, which I had not seen before. The web results for ‘Mumintrollet 1969’, though scarce, report on screaming children, making it mandatory, for all following theatre and TV adaptations, that the Mumin wear their heads and never, never again reveal the actors hiding in their bodies.</p> <p>Does this answer everything? Can I close this chapter, now? </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹At the first dinner with your parents, as you and your father got busy talking and switched to your tongue, I leaned in towards your mother and showed her the picture of Tove Jannson I have saved on my phone. In it, she swims blissfully in the water before her sanctuary in Klovrahun: immensely beautiful and serene, balancing a flower crown on her head. The water looks deep but she’s smiling. I’ve had it saved for years, I told her. </p> <p>I showed this to her to demonstrate the extent and the duration of my devotion, to retrace the same connection which, at the next dinner, a few months later, I would highlight with the unfaithful tale of my father’s trip. <span class="more_info" title=" I showed it to her as a talisman, knowing she’d understand its power, something both reminiscence and prophecy, to try to tell her that I understand, that I’m trying to understand. "> Jag visade den till henne som en slags talisman, Medveten om att hon förstår dess kraft. Både ett minne och en profetia. Att försöka få henne att förstå att jag förstår, att jag försöker förstå. </span></p> <p>And that I’ll take care of you. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹I think of you, as a baby, left outside in the Gotlandic winter to get acclimated to the cold. I don’t center my doubts that it works or even the curious, sudden memory that, as a child, I was always cold. I imagine you moving your tiny hands in the stroller, losing your soft gaze from snowflake to snowflake, falling in slow unending time. Everything moves quietly and you are not afraid; <span class="more_info" title=" you never cry. ">du gråter aldrig. </span></p> <p>No image of my childhood, real or fabricated, trasmits me this much peace. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹When I first met you, I had the feeling I knew you already. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹I want us to meet here, in this imperfection - the mess of history and timelines, us trying to make sense of it, to put the words one after the other and balance our respective powers over language. My words, your tongue. My time and your time. <span class="more_info" title=" But I trust you.">Med jag litar på dig. </span> I’m deciding to trust you. I trust that you’ll take care of me. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹<span class="more_info" title=" Time is at the heart of what I write. I guess it’s because, in a way, I’m always trying to go back.">Tiden är kärnan i det jag scriver. Jag tror att det är för att jag, på något sätt, alltid försöker resa tillbaka. </span>And the more I write, the more the old paradigm collapses: linear time and straight time, the lie that all of it points towards an absolution which, if we’re honest, will not see; that where and who you’ve been are different than the places you’ll move to and the people you will meet and become similar to. The more I become aware of this, the easier it gets for me to imagine that, maybe, forgiveness is here already, that nobody will save us and that everything is anointed; the clearer I see that the lines which extend from where I stand, anchoring themselves into the future and making waste of the past, are straight and monodirectional, that I haven’t placed them myself, that they cannot describe me or anyone I love; because the lines are actually all jumbled up, and you won’t believe where they end; because the past and the future are actually communicating vases, if you dare, and the present is more than just the place between them; because time is a road with multiple lanes and the atom crashes that ensue are those moments of wonderful clarity when you stop and think about the trajectories, the absolute causality and necessity of everything - those days of early summer, the first call of spring… </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹Do you see what I mean? </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹I’m sorry I haven’t learnt Swedish yet, baby. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹There’s a story I’ve been thinking about for a while. I never wrote down even a word for it, except for a note, titled “Mumin X Kafka”, which dates back to my last birthday. <span class="more_info" title=" Here it goes. ">Här kommer den. </span> A guy wakes up from restless dreams to find himself turned into a Mumintroll. As he looks down on his body, he finds it particularly white and soft, with a new, distinctive roundness, so he gets up to look for the mirror. In it, he finds big Mumin eyes staring back at him from a big, white Mumin head. The change is registered with a mixture of glee and terror, and the new Mumin falls back on his bed, unable to go on with his day. </p> <p>It’s the details that are hard to get down in this story - why glee, why terror? Then, is there a job the man has to attend to? Will he call in sick or commute in this new body, will it get dirty with the city’s smog? Where does this person’s consciousness reside - what crawlspace between body and mind? Which ultimately means: <span class="more_info" title=" what’s the real difference between being in a Mumin body or in a Mumin costume, when you’re not one?">vad är den egentliga skillnaden mellan känslan av att vara i en muminkropp eller i en muminkostym, när du inte är en? </span> Again, <i>just what is a Mumin?</i> I wanted it to be a story about this: finding out what it means to be a Mumin in a non-Mumin world, being exiled from Mumindalen, never having been there. </p> <p>I never wrote it down because, even stealing the tone and effect of the Metamorphosis, I couldn’t figure out a disguise effective enough to hide the obvious fact that it was a story about waking up in your childhood bed and not being the child you once were. </p> <p>In the last scene, the new Mumintrollet, having found his courage, leaves his room and takes off his Mumin head to confront his father, smoking in the kitchen, in the last hour before sunrise. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹Which words belong to whom, now? Are you stumbling over mine, will you ask me what I mean? What’s happening to my word choice, my weird English? Which words are you using - what do they remind you of, who did you speak them with? What past comes back to you now, as we mix on the page, as we spill, as we speak? </p> <p>In the world of conversations outside of here, I try to reply to your worries: it’s not about my words anymore, but ours; not my point of view, but yours - not about fidelity, or accuracy, but what happens when you bring me into your language, that house of yours I can’t access. It’s about what gets lost, yes - but also about what you can add, what and whose hands hold us, now, as we speak together. Your family, the ghost of mine, forbidding me my hometown, the tongue I thought safe. </p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹Two years ago, when I read Stockton’s essay for the first time, <span class="more_info" title=" I asked you if you were a queer child.">en gång frågade jag om du som barn var queer. </span> I forgot your answer, but it was just the beginning, fragile and necessary. More follow: how did you think of yourself? What words did you use to describe yourself? I know you don’t want to tell. I ask you to listen, then. <span class="more_info" title=" It’s much easier to talk, when I know you’re listening.">Det är så mycket lättare att prata, när jag vet att du lyssnar. </span></p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹<span class="more_info" title=" Through the story of your childhood, I get closer to mine.">MISSING </span></p> <p><br/></p> <p>🌹 I did not invent this story about Troll i kulisserna. <p>But the question is - even if I didn't invent this event, I fabricate a story around it in those anguishing days of August, as I crashed at your place because my housing contract was done and I couldn’t find anything else, when our patience for each other was so thin and so much damage was done - <i>why</i> did I do that, <i>why</i> did I feel compelled to create such a horrible thing and locate it in the space of childhood? Why don’t I remember it either?</p> <p>Why has Troll i kulisserna ingrained itself into my mind like a secondary memory, vivid though unreal - a distant relic of a childhood that wasn’t mine, not even yours, but running alongside, sideways, to the one I had?</p> <br/> [^1]: Saint Augustine, Confessions, translated by Henri Chadwick, Oxford New Classics, p.7. [^2]: Think of the jazz club in Looking for Langtson (Julien, 1989) where erotic and playful encounters between men happen. When at last the group of white rowdies, whose approach has threatened this private room multiple times throughout the movie’s eclectic and non-linear plot, breaks into the club, they find nothing and no one but smoke. [^3]: Derek Walcott, Omeros, Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 1990, p.151. </p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">barnet (hus part III)</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/konrad3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="barnet (hus part III)"/><published>2024-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/konrad3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/konrad3/"><![CDATA[<style>.popup{position:relative;display:inline-block;cursor:pointer;-webkit-user-select:none;-moz-user-select:none;-ms-user-select:none;user-select:none;display:inline}.popup .popuptext{visibility:hidden;width:160px;background-color:#555;color:#fff;text-align:center;border-radius:6px;padding:8px 0;position:absolute;z-index:1;bottom:125%;left:50%;margin-left:-80px}.popup .popuptext::after{content:"";position:absolute;top:100%;left:50%;margin-left:-5px;border-width:5px;border-style:solid;border-color:#555 transparent transparent transparent}.popup .show{visibility:visible;-webkit-animation:fadeIn 1s;animation:fadeIn 1s}@-webkit-keyframes fadeIn{from{opacity:0}to{opacity:1}}@keyframes fadeIn{from{opacity:0}to{opacity:1}}</style> <p><i>25 ‎May ‎2024, ‏‎12:37: <div class="popup" onclick="myFunction()">Du berätta aldrig om troll i kulisserna för mig.<span class="popuptext" id="myPopup">You never told me about Troll in the Wings.</span></div> I found out about it in one of those August afternoons I spent lazily browsing on my computer while you worked in the other room. The play, the second official Mumin theatre adaptation written by Tove Jansson and directed by Vivica Bandler, is known today mostly because of its beginning, in which the Mumin actors enter the stage with intact costumes to then remove their huge, fluffy heads – unmasking, amongst others, the perfectly childish smirk of Lasse Pöysti, playing Moomintrollet. This was ostensibly done to give the actors more freedom with voice and facial expressions, but a dark-internet myth has gathered around the play: children in the audience terrorized by this quasi Mumin decapitation, revealing horribly out-of-place humans inside their white, rotund bodies. In the following performances and with the TV broadcast the traumatic incident was repeated, and the play became a uniting traumatic memory for generations of Swedish children.</i></p> <p>When I started writing this in May, I wanted to talk about childhood – mine and yours, or rather, the projection of mine on yours, because you don’t like talking about the past and I try to respect that. I wrote the above paragraph first; in the following months I found myself in need of more input, and I set out to look for more information on the traumatic moment. I was hoping to see the taking-off of the masks – to hear, if not see, the children’s reaction – but I haven’t been able to find any clips of it. In the (unofficial) Mumin wiki, which my research history states I consulted, this ‘decapitation’ is mentioned without any horrific undernotes. Were children really scared? Where did I get the idea that they were? While the absence of proof solidifies the status of the event as a myth, there must’ve been another source, expanding on the story to prove, once more, the Internet’s strange passion for finding the grotesque, the uncanny, the not-quite-right, the traumatising in children’s stories. And that I hadn’t just invented it. </p> <p> You have, of course, no memory of Troll I kulisserna. You were born too late; the Mumin stories you grew up with were different, safe, an uncomplicated background: there, but never essential. <div class="popup" onclick="myFunction()">Med fanns det någon annan marginell skräck från sagor som fängslade dig när du var liten? <span class="popuptext" id="myPopup">But were there other stories of horror that captured you, when you were young?"&gt;</span></div> You became uneasy when, during one of my marathons, I showed you the Mumin ’70 anime in which Mårran appears for the first time. After asking me to press stop, you told me of how deeply unsettling it was, as a child, to see her towering over Sniff; mysterious, cold, silent. A creature one couldn’t make sense of, couldn’t speak to. Did you have to distinguish between what your eyes just saw and the child’s memory, enlarged, made stranger against the backdrop of your mind?</p> <p> Whether I came up with it or someone else, what feelings, fake or real, were activated and subsumed into the memory of the Mumin beheading, as it was passed on, shared, confused, installed in the precarious architecture of recollection - which <div class="popup" onclick="myFunction()">«njutningar och fasor»<span class="popuptext" id="myPopup">pleasures and terrors"&gt;</span></div>, otherwise unspeakable, found their expression in it?</p> <script>function myFunction(){document.getElementById("myPopup").classList.toggle("show")}</script>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">after the exhibition (october 2023/september 2024)</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/aftertheexhibition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="after the exhibition (october 2023/september 2024)"/><published>2024-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/aftertheexhibition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/aftertheexhibition/"><![CDATA[<style>img{float:left;border:0 dotted black;margin:0 20px 0 5px}body{text-alignment:justified</style> <p>What came back to me after I read his story out loud, overwhelmed with emotion, or later coagulated around it:</p> <ul> <img src="https://marialaurids.net/assets/blog_posts/posts/aftertheexhibition.jpeg.jpg" alt="A space aside inside of a partly lit underground garage. The space is enveloped by curtains with white and blue hues." width="50%" height="50%"/> <li>I feel that loving writing is constantly failing at the thing you love.</li> <li>The magic of us, what we can do together.</li> <li>Prague in February, when I was alone but I knew that someone was waiting for me back in Berlin, in the room where the apple tree that Steve gave me will, surprisingly, survive a whole winter, a bit of spring too. The last months before leaving home: all of its beauty and terror, the long hours of preparations, the time carved away for my friends. The last week, singing at the night with I., the hours at the bar, which advanced slowly; the month I lived with B. and I felt the pull to stay, to move in a little closer. Beginning of an October past, when F. came to visit and we walked along the same life for a little while again. The morning I’ll arrive in Paris, battered and confused, and S. will pick me up from the station and organize a huge breakfast that will go on for hours; days later, when I’ll smoke with F. on the balcony and try to explain the kind of life I’m preparing, what still scares me. What came out of the exhibition – it will be too early for this, and I will fail, again.</li> <li>The sunlit evenings of the first lockdown, when I forced myself to write every night and something came out of that, too, even if it didn’t have to. </li> <li>The night out when me and Coco rejoiced over learning that we had used the same word to describe the particular electricity of the exhibition, <i>magic</i>. Not an uncommon word, maybe not one a writer should use proudly. But I was drunk and sentimental that evening and I must protect that feeling, too: the wonder of having carved the same word to describe the same time - a tautology of magic, inspiring, confirming itself.</li> <li>Writing the first draft of this and trying (without success) to define a difference between remembering and reminiscing.</li> <li>I’ve interlaced my heart with yours. Doesn’t matter for how long. Ribbons of yours are woven in with mine. Traces; I hope you feel the same. </li> <li>Thinking a lot about memory, my hometowns. In the first year in Berlin I missed the sea the most and I tried to make the first image of my previous life out of it – gathering lines of poems, pictures real and imagined, the words of friends, too, born by the sea, to make a figure of my own. All along the sea was there, unchanged, with the after-image of me and my brother staring out into it before he left. Me, wondering when meaning would kick into place, fill in the experience. I remember the narrow, internal streets of Pozzuoli – the ample ones of Naples, opening (with a gasp) towards a sudden sky, the sea. What does missing mean? It’s only the heart adjusting. In my first months, I lied to it and let myself reminisce, promising to come back, until it didn’t matter anymore. Corners of Berlin make me cry, now. Every time I walk along Potsdamer Strasse I think of you, of us. The time me and Agata walked three or four bus stations from the Kunstraum and talked about twins and doubles of many kinds and it was sweet to have someone to speak in Italian with.</li> <li>I’ve tried to talk to each of them about the specific shape of this magic. This is what I’ve landed on: the magic was the magic. <i>You should’ve been there</i>. This magic was the magic of us. Of our time: the days of our meeting, the few months we shared, that sacred week before the opening. This magic was the magic of us, doing the thing we love. The magic was us and emanated all around from us and it came and went in waves, because pure feeling is unsustainable, but never went away. I remember blue make-up powder being put in a old salad bowl and then shared. The kitchen, our retreat, which Richie’s costumes made into a backstage, a theatre of its own. Then we went into the exhibition. </li> <li>You must develop a technique. Then you must develop another. You must have a method for summoning and you must not abuse it. You must learn how to distinguish between what must be summoned and what suffices to be recalled or imagined. Don’t call what doesn’t need to called. <i>Dream new dreams</i>. </li> <li>The magic reached its peak in two moments: when I read Tommaso’s words for the second time, after Véra instructed me on how to gather my words. Then, afterwards, when we hosted the second guided tours for strangers who would, in one day, see three or four exhibitions, who knows how many labours of love. We guided them and I felt like, for how much we tried, for how much they wanted to, they’d never be part of the magic, because it belonged to us, it emerged from these months of contact, the daily company in the week of the installation. And I felt we were like children of the same kind, strange and aslant, swimming around in a tight pack, in and out of the swarming schools of strangers, as we hyped up those for whom the time had come to explain their work (with words reasonable and intimate enough), until the moment was over, the light moved to the next piece and we reabsorbed into our group to be congratulated and held. Always a good word, always a work of love. We all hugged in front of Eze's glass trinkets, reflecting complex lights, or maybe not at all.</li> <li>When I called Mattia the last morning of the installation because nothing worked and I was ashamed of being so unprofessional and in the same room with you all he calmed me down and promised me <i>we</i>’d find a way. Mascha helped me put up the pages, stayed with me, patient and with unshakable faith in the success of our endeavour. </li> <li>The last day, before we had to leave, I went and sat down in Lu and Coco’s embryonal space. I closed my eyes, I let the sounds of water and whispers align my breath into a kinder rhythm. I made space for memory, for being there. </li> <li>I knew that something in my heart had shifted (like an old cosmic mechanism commanding the eclipse and the seasons of the moon) as I read the last words of Tommaso. I knew then that, despite my imprecisions, my rushing, my shortcomings, the slips of my pen and my mouth, despite myself, that Tommaso is alive, that he had made it through, that the ritual had been successful.</li> <li>I realized last week, getting sentimental again with Lula, that I’m not done talking about this. I don’t want to exhaust the magic, to say it all. </li> <li>Happiness is honey dripping into the heart. I move around our group like a zealot (in the blue coat Jean-Noël said made me look like a gay wizard), I want to know of everyone, I need everyone of us to know; then I step out of our swarm to see my friends, my boyfriend, to send messages to the absent and the unwilling, because I need to tell everyone that the magic was happiness and I found out that happiness gifts time back.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">storia di tommaso (september 2023)</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/storia-di-tommaso/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="storia di tommaso (september 2023)"/><published>2024-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/storia%20di%20tommaso</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/storia-di-tommaso/"><![CDATA[<p>Exhibition with <a href="https://www.agatahoerttrich.com/queerthingstaketime">Agata Hörttrich</a>, Coco Wiss, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/ezehyon/">Ezequiel Hyon</a>, <a href="https://bueronoelle.com/">Jean-Noël Teschauer</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/jilschuberth/">Jil Schuberth</a>, Lu Herbst, <a href="http://lulabornhak.com/">Lula Bornhak</a>, <a href="https://majazagorska.com/">Maja Zagórska</a>, Mascha Naumann, <a href="https://mattiafriso.com/">Mattia Friso</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/targetlady/">Richard Müller</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/scek_art/">Steve C.E. Knoll</a> and <a href="https://veramariedeubner.com/">Véra Marie Deubner</a>.</p> <p>Storia di Tommaso is a performative story that attempts to tell a queer narrative of becoming, finding identity and purpose outside of the frames of linear storytelling and timelines. Result of the Queer Things Take Time workshop and exhibited in the omonimous exhibition in September 2023, it is a novella informed by concepts of queer temporalities. Set in the first part of the 20th century in South Tyrol, the story is told over multiple languages and perspectives of witnesses to one man’s story who, during the Italian colonisation of the land and its subsequent attack on Ethiopia, tried to define himself across the the frames and temporalities of Christianity and Italianess.</p> <p><em>First cluster: prologue / part V: the gospel of Tommaso / epilogue</em></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster1-1.JPG-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster1-1.JPG-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster1-1.JPG-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster1-1.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Introduction and conclusion to the story with words from the heart of the story, Tommaso's perspective. Installation with writing desk: candle, writing machine, writing paper, portrait and devotional image. Chair, jacket, and string from which the pages hung. At the side of the typewriter, a page invited comments and especially continuations of the story. Some five additions were made by visitors and hung alongside the other pages. </div> <p><em>Second cluster: part I: days of halcyon / part II: body</em></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster2-1.JPG-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster2-1.JPG-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster2-1.JPG-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster2-1.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Tommaso and Johannes' childhood in South Tyrol. Account by Johannes in German, mine in English. Arranged in a tree-like pattern, growing 'sideways'. </div> <p><em>Third cluster - part IV: Bekehrung</em></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster3-1.JPG-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster3-1.JPG-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster3-1.JPG-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/qttt-cluster3-1.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Three accounts of Tommaso's conversion in German, English, Italian. Arranged in a spiral-like movement. </div> <p>Collages for the collective <em>Queer Things Take Time zine booklet</em>, one for each session of the workshop: queer apocalypse; queer childhood; queering the archive; queering the public space.</p> <div class="row mt-4"> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine1-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine1-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine2-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine2-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine3-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine3-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine3-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine4-480.webp 480w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine4-800.webp 800w,/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine4-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/blog_posts/posts/zine4.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exhibition with Agata Hörttrich, Coco Wiss, Ezequiel Hyon, Jean-Noël Teschauer, Jil Schuberth, Lu Herbst, Lula Bornhak, Maja Zagórska, Mascha Naumann, Mattia Friso, Richard Müller, Steve C.E. Knoll and Véra Marie Deubner.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">invocation - autofiction * (may 2023)</title><link href="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/invocation-autofiction-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="invocation - autofiction * (may 2023)"/><published>2024-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/invocation-autofiction-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pinetree27.github.io/blog/2024/invocation-autofiction-1/"><![CDATA[<p>You wake up in the middle of the night – my long-time friend, my other half. You wake in the middle of the night because something has broken the rhythm of your sleep: a distant howl, maybe, a call for some closeness that you too can feel, a sudden thirst. Somebody walks by in the corridor and their approach takes you out of the dream, takes you by surprise when you’re still unable to defend yourself. Now you’re afraid that something is coming and that you cannot stop it and this fear plunges you underwater, where you cannot breathe. But the steps continue beyond your door, and you’re safe again. You could try and sleep some more– you feel the temptation of being lulled back into that sweet nothingness where you don’t have to question your desires and where the memory and fantasies of the boy you once were blend together. But something of the dream’s horniness has stayed with you, and it keeps you awake – a vibration in your body, a distinct arousal; a desire to move the sheets. You wish to come back to that state of youthful bliss, but it’s too late, your mind is slowly finding its way back to you. It now catches up on what your body already knew: that warmth close to you. Something of the dream’s infinite possibilities has stuck with you and you start remembering your dream, green glass shards of a story that first disgusts, then excites you. Memories of the evening that was and the fantasies you have kept inside of you so long, no one to confide them to.</p> <p>over at <a href="https://translucentgreenplasticpress.com/invocation-autofiction-1/"><em>translucent green plastic press</em></a>. Edited by Jonah Lubin and Mona Thierse. Published 08 May 2023.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You wake up in the middle of the night – my long-time friend, my other half. You wake in the middle of the night because something has broken the rhythm of your sleep: a distant howl, maybe, a call for some closeness that you too can feel, a sudden thirst. Somebody walks by in the corridor and their approach takes you out of the dream, takes you by surprise when you’re still unable to defend yourself. Now you’re afraid that something is coming and that you cannot stop it and this fear plunges you underwater, where you cannot breathe. But the steps continue beyond your door, and you’re safe again. You could try and sleep some more– you feel the temptation of being lulled back into that sweet nothingness where you don’t have to question your desires and where the memory and fantasies of the boy you once were blend together. But something of the dream’s horniness has stayed with you, and it keeps you awake – a vibration in your body, a distinct arousal; a desire to move the sheets. You wish to come back to that state of youthful bliss, but it’s too late, your mind is slowly finding its way back to you. It now catches up on what your body already knew: that warmth close to you. Something of the dream’s infinite possibilities has stuck with you and you start remembering your dream, green glass shards of a story that first disgusts, then excites you. Memories of the evening that was and the fantasies you have kept inside of you so long, no one to confide them to.]]></summary></entry></feed>